Mayank: Cool. Hey, everyone. Very good morning. Excuse me. Sorry, I was trying to set something up. Yeah, I think we should be good to begin.
Mayank: I'm just kidding.
Mayank: Great. So I think we can start, you know, fresh today, find a good sleep. So thanks for that.
Mayank: But I also wake up a lot early, right? Everyone. So I was waiting because today I wanted to make sure everyone joins, since we have our first class for MCP, so that would be helpful. Let's start with that understanding now. So let me share my screen. Panjit, let me also do a few things. please share your CVs everyone before today.
Mayank: because I will be again going through them. Many of you did send me the CV, but again, did not follow the advice of how I have to send it. So if you can send with the proper way I asked you, that would be helpful. Many people have just sent their CV, asked me to notice what role do I want. So that would be difficult. Okay. So would be really great if you can help me with that.
Mayank: So MCP starts today is the date of 23rd. Okay, cool. TK, cloud learning so far interesting. Yes, it will be good. And don't worry, it will be updated next week. This week it will be updated a lot, hopefully. Hopefully. At least five, seven hours of new content is there. And.
Mayank: Yep, let's start everyone. Okay, cool. Before I start, anyone has any doubt from yesterday's class? Anything which is not clear?
Mayank: Before I start? Anything which is not clear?
Mayank: Great. In view of that, everyone, just one thing which I would like to quickly help you revise, and for that, what I can do is I can go to Luncheon.
Mayank: Yes. So, one quick thing just so that you don't forget it. This is according to Claude and normally as well, the difference between state and the context in runtime. So, yesterday we did these topics, right, everyone? I hope all of you remember that we yesterday discussed about state and context in runtime.
Mayank: Now, overall, of course, the same is very, very helpful, and the whole approach is that how you have to make sure that you understand them. But yes, this is the difference between the state and the context in runtime. So, this was discussed during Q&A. I forget after the break. So, state is mutable. Mutable means that it can be edited out, like it can be changed over time, right? Mutate. So, X-Men, I think, mutations.
Mayank: Context is not persistent across turns for the same thread ID. I hope you remember that when we have a memory saver and then we use a thread ID in the configuration, state is persistent. Context is not. It is just whenever you are invoking it, invoking your agent, it has to be sent fresh. And that was actually written like very subtly. It was written as well if I go on runtime.
Mayank: If you go on runtime C, runtime context provides dependency injection for your tools and middleware. Instead of hard coding values or using global state, you can inject runtime dependency like these when invoking your agent. This makes your tools more testable, reusable, and flexible. So every time you are invoking your agent, that is where it is used. So very subtle but important thing.
Mayank: And I think majorly, next things you can just read about it. Set by tools or middleware returning updates. Tools or middleware can update the state. Context, we set the context, okay? We are the one who set the context in runtime. Then, how it is declared, how it can be read. Runtime dot state, I think this is wrong. Ideally, this is not the right approach. We normally read it. In tool, yes. In tool, it is tool runtime, okay?
Mayank: In tool we get the tool runtime. So this is fine.
Mayank: Tool runtime. In the tool runtime, we are having this state and context. Then examples, I think, of things which you should set. I hope this thing is clear, everyone. Now I hope this thing is clear as well.
Mayank: Great. So now let's move forward everyone. Today we will start with a very new and important topic. A topic which I like a lot. A topic which is pretty awesome in its way. And which as well we are going to discuss in depth. So yeah, that should be everything.
Mayank: Just give me a minute.
Mayank: Great. So, let us now start, everyone. Yes, I will be giving the coupons and everything, so that should be fine. State is in runtime or not? So, no, revise the class. It is not. Okay. What is the state and context schema? again, for people who are asking this question, please revise the class. let me name myself to Mayank so that you don't have to tag start at 8 or 12. Okay, great. now let me showcase your page as well. So, pay attention, everyone.
Mayank: This is the page. MCP starts 23rd, so there is a very good gap in between the pages. 22nd August, all the resources are uploaded. GitHub, I will update by two, three days, okay? But I will ask any of you to just have the, create the PRs maybe, so that would be helpful maybe in future. But yes, anyway, that I will update.
Mayank: Yeah, I think we can start. So today, everyone, we are going to start with a very, very important topic that's actually going to be very much in depth. So the topic name is MCP Model Context Protocol. Let me get it like this here. Cool. So a few things before I begin, everyone, which I want each and every one of you to focus and understand properly. First thing.
Mayank: We are going to cover MCP in depth. I think this is something which we have discussed already. So I'm not going to teach you MCP with respect to LangChain. I'm going to teach you MCP otherwise so that you can create your own MCP server. You can create your own MCP client, MCP gateways. You can even.
Mayank: host or push your MCP servers. So when you go on, let's say, pypy, and if you search on MCPs, you can get MCP servers, and we will see that how can we create packages, etc, and make sure that everyone can use it as well, okay? So that is something which we will be learning.
Mayank: It will take around three classes easily, around three. It can take four as well, but I don't, I'm fine with it if you all are fine with it because I want to make sure that you understand in and out of the MCP. It's a very, very awesome piece of tech when we go inside it as well. And yes, I think then we will jump back to your LangChain everyone. So LangChain, we will be jumping back after that and then you will be set for MCP for kind of life. So that is the case. Cool.
Mayank: I hope that makes sense.
Mayank: What all I discussed? Okay. Take four as you cover in depth. Should be fine. As part of MCP helpers, resource tool, everything we will be covering. We will actually be going in depth and seeing that how this actually works. Okay. On that note, if you have not watched the LangChain classes, now I think is a very good time. So you will get two weeks at least to go through that. Okay. If you have UR based job opportunities.
Mayank: Not which I know quickly. Let me check my emails and stuff. Okay. Is launching completed? No. Like, we have to do project as well. Like, in terms of concept, you may say it is completed almost, but we have to do projects and everything. Further, we have this left. The…
Mayank: multi-agent and everything. So that is also something which is left. We are just covering MCP in depth so that you are able to actually make sense of each and everything on the right. Resources, prompts, tools, everything you are generally able to make sense. MCP is common in each framework. Yes, MCP is a standalone concept. Is MCP as important as LangChain? Yes, it depends, but MCP is important. I would not compare LangChain and MCP. That would be apple and oranges, but MCP is important.
Mayank: So if you're good with it, can I get a quick smiley face? So if you have not revised LangChain, you have awesome resources. You have awesome MindGPT. You generally have awesome notebooks as well, which I will share more. But yes, you should now revise the same in depth. That is very, very much required.
Mayank: Because once you cover things in depth, other frameworks, as I mentioned, will be pretty easy. And frameworks, these, sorry, these protocols, we also want to go in depth. Okay. With that, let's start everyone. So I hope all of you are able to see my screen. Let us quickly begin.
Mayank: Amelia's teach, I will see and provide you with the coupons, okay? I said today I got the DSA one, so hopefully that would be helpful.
Mayank: Just a minute, everyone. I'm checking one thing quickly. Recording your only case.
Mayank: Shut up. Email ID for resume I'm giving older names.
Mayank: So, everyone, now let us start with model context protocol. And as we have discussed, like every topic, we will be discussing about MCP in complete depth, so that not only are you able to understand and use MCP servers, which are provided to you by a third party, by a company, you are also able to create your own MCP servers, MCP clients, you are able to run them in a dockerized container.
Mayank: You are able to also have them published as a package so that others can use it. And not only that, because I have made sure that I have gone through the complete documentation of MCP as well, where exactly how this complete thing works, that will help you to understand that why were some design decisions taken the way they were taken, what exactly is in the backend side of MCP.
Mayank: And yes, this is a very easy concept if you understand the same properly, but at the same time, a lot difficult if we are unnecessarily confusing it with other terms, which is the case. The best part with MCP is that it is a concept. So no matter tomorrow, if we are doing LangChain, LangGraph, maybe creating simple AJITs in Python.
Mayank: in Claude desktop, in Claude app, anywhere for that matter, we will be able to use lots of our application using MCP. And again, since it is a very new kind of a technology, understanding the same in depth is very, very much required because over time, MCP is going to, like right now also it is booming, over time it's also going to make.
Mayank: a lot of use across AI applications, AI and Agentic AI applications. With that, let's quickly understand that what are the quick prerequisites. So to understand, we will be doing simple plain Vanilla Python. So that is what we are going to use everywhere. And Claude slash Claude Desktop. So since in 2026, we are having.
Mayank: Claude desktop and Claude used a lot. We will understand here and there. You don't have to purchase Claude for that. Just that you have to understand that, okay, how Claude or Claude desktop are able to use MCP applications. And otherwise, I think we are fine if we have a good knowledge of APIs as well. So that is majorly the role, everyone, which we should be aware about.
Mayank: With that, let's now start the understanding about MCP. And for this, I will actually like to take you through a complete story in the next part where we do understand that how and why MCP was needed. So the very first part, everyone, I'm calling it like why MCP had to exist, okay? So rather than how it came up and everything, why it has to actually exist. Okay, cool.
Mayank: Can you use Claude code in the VS Code? Yes, totally on you. Claude ecosystem, Koupan, Bhanme, Ravi teaching. Good, everyone. So in this, I will be teaching for 15 minutes, then I will be having that out. So let's jump back into the main approach. I think now you are comfortable with that. Okay. Again, if I ask how many of you don't have any idea what MCP is, will you teach how to use MCP using LangChain? Once you understand MCP in depth, you can use it anywhere.
Mayank: Anywhere in this complete thing, you will be able to use the same. Okay?
Mayank: Sure. If you have no idea, then it's a very good learning journey. Great. API is nyata. API is nyata. I'm sending you all a link. Okay. I am sending all of you a link. Hopefully that would be very, very helpful for all of you. Let's see.
Mayank: You see this, everyone? The link in front of you, like, sorry, a page in front of you.
Mayank: We will understand what is the protocol of MCP and all these things. See, here things are kind of discussed in a very interactive manner. I have created this. I actually have used this in one of my videos. Can you publish a video on MCP on YouTube? Yes. So more videos are coming. But anyways, everyone, you see this? It's a very interactive kind of an artifact, which I created after lots of time to make sure that actually you can understand lots of things in here.
Mayank: It is very nicely explained. It is very much in line with Claude. It explains about APIs, all these things. Though I plan to launch the video in which I will be using on next month. Okay, so the video is kind of getting recorded, but yeah, I think you all can have it. So in this APIs, AI.
Mayank: MCP is also actually very nicely explained, to be very honest. Just that it is from a non-tech side. For your batch, I don't want to limit. Like, again, the understanding is pretty fine, so it should not be a problem. Rather, I can use this as well. It's pretty good. Okay? But yeah, I'm sharing this link. If you are from tech, non-tech, any background, just revise all these things. It will be very, very important. Okay? All these topics are very, very important. The best part, genuinely, they are explained in a very easier manner. So, if you will notice.
Mayank: It is all very interactive. Everywhere it will ask you to click up so that actually you are just having step by step manner. You can move these things up to understand and everything is properly explained. Okay, so let me share it with you. Okay, so this took a lot of time for me to create. Genuinely, I have explained many things in here, as I mentioned.
Mayank: Take my word for it. So, you can go through it. It should be very helpful.
Mayank: Good. Everyone, is my voice fine?
Mayank: Cool. A, Adi, can you please check at your internet? Same for you, Sumit. Okay, I think there was a breakage in between. Let's make a second voice. Let's wait a second.
Mayank: Great. Let's continue. Okay. I've added the inequality to craft. I don't think you will miss out on anything with me, so it should be fine. Okay. Shadow. So now everyone, let us move forward and continue our discussion on MCP. And in the very first part, I would just like to exist about why MCP.
Mayank: had to exist. So MCP came into existence and why it has to exist. One thing to note, MCP is not a very old piece of tech. It is not that MCP has been there since dawn of time, like APIs or anything like MCP is relatively a very, very new framework or protocol. We can take it as a protocol.
Mayank: And it has been developed by Anthropic. So the creators of Anthropic, they only actually came up with MCP. So let's try to understand that why exactly that came up. Our story actually start with the most important thing, which I think happened in the last maybe 30, 40 years of the technology side, maybe around very comparable to the internet, okay? That is when ChatGPT was launched. So when ChatGPT was launched.
Mayank: So this I actually take as dawn of the AI era. If you will go on ChatGPT, so start of the AI era. This page I always refer to, November 30, 2022, introducing ChatGPT. And yes, this is when OpenAI gave their ChatGPT an awesome chatbot to the world.
Mayank: It actually exploded a lot in the overall usage. It gained, I think, around, if I remember right, 1 million users in around one week. And by two months or three months, it was already having around 10 million plus users. Okay, so I think I have the exact numbers as well on my notes. So talking about the same, yes, I think, yes, it got 1 million in a week.
Mayank: So around 1 million users in a week and then 100 million, I think around by three months. So these are generally the numbers which any software aim for. And this is actually a very, very big overall.
Mayank: movement for technology because maintaining these numbers, like reaching these numbers is very difficult. If you think about this, not only is it just a number, it is not like that, okay, something of a number was given, but what ChatGPT introduced was a totally new kind of way to interact with machines.
Mayank: So it was an awesome, awesome piece, as I mentioned, where you can ask something like, right now, it is a lot mature. If I can go on ChatGPT, it is genuinely a lot mature, where you have lots of features. But yes, majorly, if you send it a hi, it will be able to reply to you in a proper real time like a human. The best part was that how not only was it replying in an NLP manner, in a natural manner.
Mayank: But also how it was further able to actually be useful as well. So in a way, everyone, the way we connect with machines, okay, our relationship with machine totally transformed after coming off ChatGPT. We used to give it an answer, sorry, a question, and it used to give us an answer.
Mayank: Initially, everyone liked ChatGPT and just talked with it normally, asking silliest of the questions, asking it to write any poem or doing anything. But over time, of course, people realized that ChatGPT can also be used. ChatGPT can also be used in professional manner. What exactly is meant by the professional manner? Along with ChatGPT web.
Mayank: They also, of course, launched the ChatGPT API. So right now also, OpenAI has ChatGPT API. If you search ChatGPT API, we actually have the complete platform via which these models, these same intelligent model, they can be accessed and used inside your software or any application which we are creating.
Mayank: Till around 500 years, everyone, machine can only understand buttons or some fixed input. This was actually the very first time where after spending lots and lots of effort and complete nights, scientists were able to make sure that machine can now also understand words as well, the way we normally talk to a human. Now, let's talk about what exactly ChatGPT was. So ChatGPT was an LLM.
Mayank: which is Large Language Model. Now, I will, or before I go deep into what exactly this is, I would like to present LLM just as a black box. LLM, in a way, for most of us, at that time as well, was just like a black box. Now, what do I mean by black box? You give it an input, and.
Mayank: You can get an output. The input, everyone can be in a natural language, and you can get the output also, which is going to be in a natural language. So if you send a hi, it will send you back. Hi, Mayan. How are you? So very, very simple sense. LLM is just a black box. I hope everyone is with me till now.
Mayank: The initial ChatGPT was an LLM, okay? The initial ChatGPT was an LLM, now it has been made into an agent. And as we move ahead, you will understand why it has been, why it is an agent as of now, okay?
Mayank: Now, this I am talking about the very initial ChatGPT, which was when it was just a chatbot. You can just simply log in. Now it has, of course, been transformed a lot. So you have to just think of the very, very first iteration of ChatGPT, the one which was released on November 22, where you did not have any of the functionality, just a simple message you used to send, and you used to then get the reply back. So this is all around the ChatGPT when it was launched.
Mayank: And in a sense, we can say that LLM is just a next word or token predictor. So all my LLM is, is that if I give it a hi, it will just try to give you the reply token by token. Now, we kind of already know what a token is. So token, tokenizer, LLM, if you will.
Mayank: open this tokenizer, which is by OpenAI, you can just see, Hi, I am Mayank. So there are five tokens inside this particular sentence. And what your LLM does, everyone, is that LLM just makes sure that it is able to provide you with a particular answer, token by token. So it is a next word or token generator so that it can give you the complete answer.
Mayank: But at the same time, all it can do, or it used to do everyone, was that it was giving you the answer. It was just able to provide you with an answer. If you ask it for a code, it used to give that code to you. So you ask it for, let's say, a code. It used to make sure that it provides you with that piece of code. So let me quickly get the code icon.
Mayank: And?
Mayank: copy paste the code onto your application. Same used to happen with our poem or any other thing on that matter. So the whole idea or the approach everyone used to become that how it is just a very smart assistant. It is just a LLM which is.
Mayank: a very, very smart brain. So I normally like to say LLM as a brain, but nothing more than that. So you ask it something, it used to give you that, nothing else. If you ask it to write an email, it can write an email for you, but it cannot send the email there. Okay, so that is again where we say.
Mayank: model sorry about the LLM and we normally say that as model as well model so that is where the model context protocol the model part is coming model context protocol so model is coming from this thing so this everyone is the model which we are able to get and that is the scenario that you give it a question and it can give you the answer that is all what it can do for the time being.
Mayank: Great. Everyone, let's move forward.
Mayank: And though, of course, LLM was a very awesome piece of technology, there's a very inherent problem with us human beings. And that problem, everyone, is that we are very lazy. So I always say that human beings are very, very lazy. And that is where, again, the requirement about.
Mayank: something or our LLM able to do things came into picture. So we now want that our ChatGPT or our AI, it can not only give me the overall email, okay, it can not only give me the email for my sick leave.
Mayank: It send the same as well. So it is able to send the same as well. Again, not only provide me with the code, actually write and run it on my machine.
Mayank: machine. So this is actually the major thing that we human are very, very lazy. And one more thing which is very important to understand here is that we normally always work with a tool around us. So it will be the case everyone that we will be working either with Gmail, we might be working with Slack. So let me write down these awesome technologies, Gmail, Slack.
Mayank: Maybe we are using Word online or Google Sheets for any of these things, or we are using Outlook for our email needs or Drive. So what used to happen still that our LLM.
Mayank: It was still getting used day in and day out. So, of course, people were using it a lot. But it was still around all these applications. So, all of our applications, everyone, like, for example, Gmail. We can then have, let's say, Slack. Then we can have everyone drive. So, I can have drive here.
Mayank: Google Drive, where we can easily upload or read any file. And of course, like this, multiple applications we are having, which we can use, which we can go across. And as of now, what was happening was that in a normal day of any user, he is interacting with multiple of these tools. When he interacts with multiple of these tools.
Mayank: He used to maybe copy the file from Google Drive, then make sure that he's pasting or attaching that file into ChatGPT. ChatGPT used to give it the analysis or the summary about the file. And then we used to make sure that, OK, how the same can be sent to your Gmail or any other thing. So that was the whole idea. That was what was having, where these were all the way we were working with your AI.
Mayank: And this was a problem again because, as I mentioned, we don't want ChatGPT to tell us what to do. We don't want it to tell us what to do, but rather do the same for us because then it was still lagging behind lots of automation tools, tools which can actually get the work done.
Mayank: And that is where you can think of all these things, these applications, that's tools which your AI can use. Okay, so this is actually the case. And going back, since it is in black box, everyone.
Mayank: It doesn't actually know that, okay, how or what all are the tools and everything which we are using. So it is genuinely not having an idea that, okay, I just am a brain. It doesn't have any hands or everything. It can give you the best test of the email that, hey, this is the email which will surely get you the leave.
Mayank: But it is not aware how to send and everything. So it is just generally a brain without any hand or anything. And we have to make sure that we are able to provide it with the tools or the context. So that was the main requirement, everyone. And we have seen that how we were having so much of these different, different things. So the very first thing which we tried to fix to make the answer of.
Mayank: ChatGPT better was something known as context. So let's discuss about this quickly in the next part. But context was actually, then you will be understand how the context part of ChatGPT, sorry, MCP also comes into picture. Till now in our story, we have seen that how LLM came into being, it's a black box and how we can use or we were using it to get an answer, but not anything which was really happening. I hope this is clear, everyone.
Mayank: Anyone has any doubt? Able to stay with me till the end of the story?
Mayank: Just give me a minute. Sorry. Video off. While I teach, I try to make the video off so that you can just focus on the screen completely. let me know. I am fine with both. I can open the video. It should be fine. Okay.
Mayank: As I said, I'm fine with any of the things. Cool.
Mayank: Sure.
Mayank: Again, Rukhya, just give me 15-20 minutes, you will understand what MCP is properly, okay?
Mayank: So now, everyone, let us continue our discussion and let's now move on to understanding about the context. Our ChatGPT, and I'm going to take ChatGPT here, though, of course, MCP is a concept, as I mentioned, which can be used by every AI today, okay? And of course, that will also get clear. And even though Claude is getting used a lot, we have to make sure that how we are able to, one second, everyone.
Mayank: Cool. Actually, sorry, Arun was just got a call, actually.
Mayank: Yeah, there was a dilemma page I have to take.
Mayank: One minute.
Mayank: Great. Yeah, sorry. Just had a delivery to take. So that is what was taking the time. I will keep the video open while I will be turn it off. Okay. So I think that should be helpful and good for all. So let's start actually. My bad.
Mayank: Yes. So now everyone, let us continue our discussion with respect to context and try to understand that what exactly or where it falls. We are going to understand with ChatGPT because that is how like we started using AI. So I always use this line that ChatGPT is to AI what Google is to internet. Like that is all what started, right? Now coming to ChatGPT, it can give us a much better answer when it is having the context. So if you are asking it to.
Mayank: write an email for your Leap application, it will be able to give you a much, much better answer when it actually understands that how you write the emails and everything. And in a way, if I have to give the definition of context, context is everything that your LLM/model can see when it answers your question.
Mayank: So everything which your model can see or access when it answers your question. Now, of course, we make sure that we can give it an idea about which company we are working on, what exactly is the case. If you are asking it for a code, you can tell which way of coding you follow. So context actually, of course, matters a lot because better the context our tools have, better will be the overall answer.
Mayank: Just as a very, very good example, if you ask your AI, and this is something where you can go to ChatGPT as well, everyone, and you can just start a new chat. If we just, or let me use Claude here, because with Claude, it will be easy. If I go on Claude, everyone, and if I just take away the excess of web search.
Mayank: And maybe use a little bit older model. If I ask it, who is the president of Venezuela? Tell without searching internet. Now we will see that how, since it will try to search and get an answer, it will surely try to do that.
Mayank: But it will be giving the answer as wrong. So I can answer this from my training data where it is having a knowledge cutoff date. So all your LLMs, everyone, as I mentioned, kind of a black box, they have been trained up to a date and they just know the answer based on that. So it is saying Nicholas Maduro has been the president of Peninsula. Since you asked not to search, of course the answer is wrong. If I quickly search, I think all of us would know that this is not the truth.
Mayank: But without the context, the answer would be wrong. So we know that he was taken away forcefully, former union leader and former politician. And if the second I give it the context to search the web, try again, this time because I have opened the search web, see, I think yes, it is asking me for the question and stuff. So I could just mention search internet and then answer.
Mayank: So now if you will notice everyone, it is searching the internet, it will get all the answer and now it will give the right answer. So a very, very small demo, but this demo kind of proves that how with a context, overall the answer which you get is a much better. And as we see in the last approach, we were using and providing ChatGPT with the context, our Slack message, information about our project, who our manager is, what is the work we do.
Mayank: So that ChatGPT can give us with a much better answer. So that was the whole understanding. And that is a very, very important reason that MCP has context in its name. Okay. This was MCP is not about giving, so I will write down this line. MCP is not about giving our LLM more intelligence. It is about.
Mayank: giving it an ability to see more. So this is the reason everyone MCP is having context in its name. So model we have seen, context also we have seen. Now let's try to understand the last term as well. And this is where this whole thing will make a lot of sense. And we will understand that again, okay, what exactly happened?
Mayank: in the next part that why it was able to come up and how actually we gradually move towards the MCP requirement. So now everyone, let's continue our discussion and try to understand for the same. If we quickly just understand we were having our ChatGPT, the very first thing that ChatGPT gave was it gave us the ability to write and make a function call. Function call.
Mayank: So what used to happen? You used to tell your AI that, hey, we can actually bind tools to our LLM. So if you're having an LLM, every LLM allows us to bind the tools. And then it can tell us that, okay, this is the tool, everyone, which we have to use to get the work done. As a very simple example, we can give it a web search tool, just like we saw in the example.
Mayank: So that it can get the research from the web search. Similarly, everyone, we can give it a tool to read emails, which can be done via Gmail. So easily, it can be done via Gmail. Because ideally, these are all the functions. So all of these things which we were doing, everyone, they were also just some APIs or action which we can perform in our day-to-day application. Talk about Slack.
Mayank: We have something known as read messages. So we have something known as read messages in Slack.
Mayank: Then similarly, everyone, we can get the files and everything. So slowly and slowly, what happened now is that since ChatGPT, and I think it was somewhere around 23 when it allowed, so mid 23, OpenAI actually shipped, this thing because it actually get the gap that, hey, people want to.
Mayank: Make sure that they can interact with their tools. They are not using AI just for getting the answers, but now to do some real work as well. So the idea, everyone, was that give your AI model a list of functions it is allowed to call, describe what each and every one of that does, and now your AI.
Mayank: It will actually be able to run those functions. So again, the whole approach was that it can tell you that, hey, what exactly has to be run, and it can make sure that then it can get the complete context. For example, if you ask it for President of Venezuela, it can tell you that, hey, if you can search this query on Google or any AI, President of Venezuela.
Mayank: and give me the results, I can give you a better answer. I will have the context and I will give you a better answer. Now, in here, everyone, one thing to note, okay, is that LLM does not used to run the tool itself. What do I mean by that? When it kind of got started, it was still either running it in a separate machine or it asks you to run it on a machine. So LLM never runs the code itself.
Mayank: It actually just provides you that these are the arguments with which I want you to run. We used to describe each and every function, and then it used to tell that, okay, I need to read your emails from this date to this date. So that is how it used to happen. And actually, it is the case even now as well. If I go again to, say, ChatGPT, just as a very basic example, sorry, to Claude.
Mayank: will notice everyone that when I ask it, "Can you check my calendar from 30th to 10th September and tell if I have any event?" Now, we will notice everyone when I ask this particular request, it will actually tell or go through.
Mayank: My calendar. So, it will be trying to hit up a tool. See, let me search the correct Google calendar. I think we have disabled the same. Let me give the same IMI access and say try again. Try again. And in that manner, everyone, okay, I think I will have to refresh it so that it can be loaded. It is giving me some command for the same. It should not give. Let me open a new chat. Ask it.
Mayank: Can you search if I have any meetings from September 10th to 20th? Let me just make sure that I'm having the and I'm having the Sonnet. And we can now run this. It will understand that, OK, it has to use the calendar because it is having the access to it.
Mayank: Then it will try to run it with some arguments. So very much close to how we have real APIC. It actually sent all these things. Start time, end time, time zone, order by, and page size. So it is saying that no events are found on your calendar. Your calendar looks clean, but it actually made a request to everyone. And this is actually how your function calling also used to work, that you used to give it some functions. And your.
Mayank: LLM or your model, it used to call up those functions. And that actually solved a problem for a bit. And now moving forward, everyone, these actions I will refer to as tools. So you can say that there is a web search tool, there is a read email tool. And the problem which arise was that now as we move ahead, everyone like this feature, game changer, this was a lot time saving. But.
Mayank: Everyone now started adding or creating their own sets of tools. So each and everyone, they started creating and adding their own set of tools into their ChatGPT or their LLM. And though it solved the problem for a while, so again.
Mayank: Their ChatGPT, it was able to become a lot better. It was able to actually act. It actually kind of felt magic for the first time that, hey, now I don't have to copy-paste anything. My AI is smart enough that it can now tell me that, hey, this is what I want to have with my own hand-built tool.
Mayank: So instead of me doing five manual copy paste, we just say that, hey, go check my calendar just like I did. It can itself tell you that, hey, this is what I want to run the calendar tool with, and it can then give you the answer. So it can check the transaction log, look up at the error code, and it can actually now coming in the territory of being useful in my day to day application as well. So tools give the overall ability to my AI to act as well.
Mayank: And for a time being, it kind of meant that, hey, the problem seems to be solved. But again, the solution was very short lived and that we will quickly discuss that why it was short lived and we will try to understand the same again, that what exactly made the solution short lived. I hope this understanding is also clear, everyone. Anyone has any doubt? What is different between MCP and tool? I think that will just get clear, just 10, 15 minutes more.
Mayank: Just taking a little bit longer approach so that you are able to relate to the story and you can explain to someone as well that why it is needed. Okay. Great.
Mayank: Any doubt anyone before I move forward?
Mayank: Can you help me understand the difference between API and MCP? API and MCP. Mobi, just give me a minute. Okay, it will be clear. Why protocol? Just let's continue now. Yeah, sure.
Mayank: So now, everyone, let's continue and understand that why this solved problem briefly and why it was not the exact fix. One thing to note, whatever I'm calling this as a tool, and this is where your vocabulary should be very much clear, this tool, everyone, you can call it as an action.
Mayank: And in the backend, it is an API being called. So if you think about this, this read email, it is an API which Gmail provides. So when we were giving our ChatGPT a function, and actually OpenAI released this feature where it said that, hey, you can use our.
Mayank: read email API, you can connect it with ChatGPT as a function. ChatGPT will tell that how it wants to run it. And if I show you quickly, I can just see calendar API, Google, Google Calendar API overview, quick start. Let's say.
Mayank: What all? Yeah. So if you will see there are create event. So there is a create event API everyone. Similarly, there is list event. All these are different, different endpoints which are available, which we can run like this start time, end time. And that is what we meant that in mid 2023, we are able to give our AI the approach of calling these tools, okay, or calling these functions or actions.
Mayank: But the problem arise everyone that now it solve the problem at an individual level, but for a company level or when it scales, it again became a problem. Just think about if your company runs three different AI assistant, a general chatbot, let's say for everyone, a coding assistant for developers, and let's say an analytic assistant for the data team. And it used to touch base on 20 of the tools. It used to connect with 20 of the tools.
Mayank: This is where the problem became a lot bigger, because now you will have to make sure that you are maintaining this yourself. So still, you have to make sure that you are able to use AI. That is non-negotiable. Your AI should be able to connect with these tools to perform the action. But in a very simple company as well, there were now easily lots and lots of tools. Just as a very basic example, if I take four applications.
Mayank: And say that in all those four applications, there are just six actions which I need to perform. This is easily 24 tools I'm looking forward to. And I, as a user, will be maintaining, will be making sure that, okay, the tool works.
Mayank: handling all the authentication for all those 24 tools, handling the way these tools should be told to AI. So the problem became that now every function needed its own method, its own data format, its own error handling. We have to maintain the same everyone. We have to make sure that they are secure. And though we started using AI and connected tools to save time, now we are spending that same time to.
Mayank: Maintain our tools. Maintain our tools. Because over time, it will surely happen that some tools will change in the backend. They will require some other information. And that was the exact problem which each and every one of us saw. And yeah, that became a nightmare because now we said to make one job easier, but we actually ended up creating a whole new type of a job, which is.
Mayank: just to make our shortcut running. So we found a shorter way, but now we need a complete, complete thing to make the shortcut running. And this is where everyone now MCP came up and why MCP has to exist. Anthropic saw this problem and it understood that, hey, this is generally a problem which needs to be solved. And yes, every company would love that if this thing can be solved very nicely.
Mayank: What Anthropic said was that, hey, if we can create a protocol via which, and again, it's a complete new protocol, just like how we have HTTP for web and others, we can create a server.
Mayank: which can connect with our AI application, hence the protocol. In future, we will see what are the different points and everything. But if we are able to come up with this complete thing that we are, Gmail will say that, hey, this is my MCP server. It will be maintained by Gmail. It will have all the tools. Along with tools, it will have resources and prompt as well. So these are the three things which MCP provides.
Mayank: And if now our application can connect to this server and just tell the action what it wants to perform. For example, your ChatGPT or your LLM this time will tell this Gmail MCP server, which will be a collection of tools. So this everyone will be lots and lots of tools, send email, read email, create draft, create a tag.
Mayank: delete a particular tag, archive an email, delete an email, read a message, send a message, archive a chat. Then there is something known as prompt and resources as well, which we will learn. But if, and these are known as MCP primitives, all MCP provides, if my Gmail MCP server is having all these things, then I could just connect that server to my.
Mayank: AI. Once it gets connected, everyone, then we can make sure that all these actions, all these tools, along with few other things, can directly be taken up with my overall MCP only. So now the heavy lifting, all the development, all the maintenance has been moved out and is being done by this MCP server. This I could kind of say as client, okay? So it's a client server architecture at the end of the day.
Mayank: And now what I can do, everyone, I just have my ChatGPT, or any AI for that matter, and I could just connect the MCP servers of the tool I want to use. So if you want to use Gmail, just connect the Gmail MCP server. So this can be for Gmail. If you want to use Slack, just connect the Slack one to your ChatGPT. It will be able to use Slack. If you want to connect, let's say, your Drive.
Mayank: Just connect the same related to drive, drive, and it will be able to connect. You are not actually worrying about how exactly these things work. You generally don't care how these things are having. If you are having, let's say, any database, maybe SQL DB or anything, just give it a DB. Internally, these will be all the actions and tools. Your ChatGPT will just tell that, hey, this is what I want to do.
Mayank: And all the heavy lifting, all the part of doing this stays with your MCP servers, not with you. So in a way, by creating this thing — and this is where we have the official MCP documentation as well, everyone — is an open source standard for connecting AI applications to external systems. Now, if you think about this, this is a complete server, everyone, which is having our applications.
Mayank: Sorry, which is having a system. This language, the way they are able to connect is known as MCP, Model Context Protocol. Now your model, it can get a protocol, get a context. The protocol or the language is MCP, and it can then do the work. So pay attention.
Mayank: MCP is the open source standard for connecting AI application to external systems. Using MCP, AI application like Claude or ChatGPT can connect to data sources, local files, databases, tools, search engines, calculators, and workflows, specialized prompts, so as I mentioned, enabling them to access key information and perform task.
Mayank: Now, normally people explain MCP with a USB-C port, but I don't actually like this explanation because it tries to sometimes oversimplify it and then make it.
Mayank: very difficult to follow. But in my case, this is how you have to think about MCP. So MCP is a collection of tools, because 99% of the times we are using tools or action in our server, which allows our AI to have hands and perform actions on the applications with which we are connecting. So in a way, APIs, we already had those, around those we create our tools or actions.
Mayank: tools or actions. And then when we combine multiple of these tools and actions and gave AI a way to call them, that is where MCP came into picture. Now, the best part, again, you don't have to worry about any of the updates. You don't have to actually worry about how exactly these things are happening. But the benefit, if you think about that, why MCP has to exist and why it is allowed is that.
Mayank: Even in my Claude, everyone, this thing, these connectors are done by MCP. If you want to add a custom connector, it will ask you to give a remote MCP server URL. So think about this, any application which wants to get integrated with AI, and in today's world, that is all the application, because as I mentioned in the very starting, this software did not just introduce a new.
Mayank: Basic software, it changed the way we work with softwares. Now, moving forward, people will not be writing code to all tools. They will genuinely be asking AI, being lazy, that, hey, write an email to my manager. And now, if you will notice, everyone, MCP is giving you a way through which the AI application can connect with your apps.
Mayank: The better MCP server an application will have, the better it will be able to get integrated into AI, the better it will be used across different use cases, and this will be a lot better, right? So it is spreading a lot faster because actually it is just more than a nice idea, okay? It is what makes your application usable.
Mayank: Now, just as an example, if GitHub is not having an MCP server, people will not be able to use GitHub. And it may happen that people move on to some other software which is supporting these MCP servers. So in a way, everyone, this is actually what MCP does, where it allows your applications, your AI application, which was just a black box, which was just a brain, it provides hands to your overall AI applications. I hope this is clear, everyone.
Mayank: Now, I hope this is clear, MCP. Who created MCP servers? We can create as well because it's an open source one, but companies maintain them. We can create the same as well.
Mayank: You have 25 to 30 APIs to maintain. Don't you think it's a problem? Don't you think it's a problem?
Mayank: Same thing, OK.
Mayank: MCP is just a REST client. On a very bigger scale, you can understand it like this, but it is more than that. Okay, it is more than that. How is it different from a typical REST API? Typical REST APIs, we have to add, we have to tell how to call. MCP is a totally new protocol. It is faster. Is it faster? No, it's different. So that is the language. It is different. Okay.
Mayank: How is it different than RAG? I believe when I will explain RAG, I will explain it, but RAG is a totally different way of providing context, okay? Why it is like a protocol, that we will discuss as well, like why it's a protocol and what exactly a protocol is. Can you summarize the long story short? AI was just a brain. We needed to use hands, and for that, we came up with tools, and then we came up with applications, okay?
Mayank: Cool. If they are providing or maintaining their MCP servers and we are connecting there, then what will be the use of making our own MCP server? So, kapil, if you are having any application which is in your company, you will need to have the MCP servers which you use, right? No one is going to create that. Further, many times we need an MCP server which is having less number of tools, which is having different varied tools as well. So that is why we need them. Okay.
Mayank: They're asking you like a ChatGPT. API is a single tool. MCP is a connection of tools. In a very simple sense, yes, but as we move ahead, it will change and move a lot away from that definition. In your project, are we creating MCP or using tool providers? We are going to create MCPs. Through MCP, can we connect to any web application and mobile application? If the MCP is available, then you can do that. Can we consider MCP as an orchestrator? No.
Mayank: Sound like a pleasure of tools which will be called when API is used. Kind of like that. Is there are too many tools like Gmail, Outlook, Hotmail worth? Won't it confuse the agent? It depends. We can provide a very good summarization or description of our tools, then it will not. What is the use of MCP server when it will be used in real application? You see this connector, Vinay?
Mayank: All these different different connectors, these are MCP servers only. So if it is not present, you will understand the use. Your chat GPT would just be like a, your AI would just be like a normal chat GPT or AI, the problem which we faced. Okay.
Mayank: Okay, cool. Does MCP like as a mediator? No. Do we need to provide argument when we call MCP? Yes. Is Gmail connected? Takes money from ChatGPT to use its data? No. What's the difference between RAG and MCP? RAG is totally different. RAG is a different way of connecting the context. Okay, MCP host client, we will come. That is the architecture of MCP. So without MCP, we cannot send email like in Gmail. No, you cannot. You will have to provide a tool rather than, okay.
Mayank: How does compliance is maintained in MCP just like any server or any protocol? Nothing else. Okay. Do you cover RAG afterwards? Not right now. What would the agreement with agent and MCP provider? They must be paying them heaps as well. No, you're not. Why most of the people ask about APIs and confusing with MCP. Is it really working like APIs work? Kind of. MCP servers are calling those APIs. So let me come to that now. Okay.
Mayank: What if you want to connect the APIs for which MCP server is not created? Create an MCP server for that. We will be learning how to create that because providing them by tool is not supported by AI. MCP interact with other systems, Gmail to send email. We can replace it with our tool as well using Gmail API. Yeah, you can do that. Should not be a problem. You can create MCP for your case. MCP is only required for other party tools like Gmail. For our own tools, we can use LangChain tools. Is that right? Partially.
Mayank: You can create an MCP servers for your tools as well. That's much better. Okay. MCP have the same syntax everywhere or different app. It's same. It's the same protocol. So protocols are having the same syntax. Okay. Why MCP is better than tools, I think. Okay, let me, let me move forward. Then I think I will explain the same. It will be much better. Okay. So let me move forward everyone and then let's, then these questions will also be answered. So don't worry on that. Okay. Few of the things will be answered.
Mayank: I thought that the way we are covering things in depth, many of these things will be clear, but please revise the classes, what should be fine. So, now everyone, let us move forward and try to continue our discussion. Just let's see a few of the things around our MCP architecture, though we will be discussing that in depth, and not the architecture or other, I would like to say it as components here. When I talk about MCP components, everyone, it is a very similar kind of a host.
Mayank: server kind of a case. So, where we are having a host and where we are having a server. Now, there is something known as client as well, but we will discuss and talk about the expanded architecture as we move forward because we will be covering that in depth. But for the timing, it's just a very simple host, sorry, my bad, it is a very simple client-server architecture. So, there is host, client, and server. Okay, three things are there, everyone.
Mayank: We have been using client server architecture kind of, I guess, for our whole life, where we have a client which is going to hit an API. That API is living on a server, and we are getting back the results which we can use. Now, to make sure that this MCP server can give us an answer, we use an MCP client. They speak the same language.
Mayank: And that is the reason that they are able to genuinely interact with one another and get the data and the output right. So in a way, everyone, if you are having, let's say, ChatGPT, I provide it with the MCP client, and now my ChatGPT, it can connect with any MCP server.
Mayank: It can connect with any MCP server and just get us the results. And of course, this is a protocol, just like HTTP, hypertext transfer protocol, FTP, file transfer protocol. They should speak the same language. What language that is, Mayank, is it REST or any other thing we will discuss in depth, but they should speak the same language.
Mayank: Now, there are two kinds of MCP servers as well. Again, as I said, we will be seeing and discussing this in depth. One is your STDIO, standard input output. Second, everyone, is streamable HTTP. So, earlier it was HTTP plus SSE, but now it has been deprecated, last I checked in the official documentation.
Mayank: I can quickly search for it. I think it has been just depreciated this year only. Can you tell me when HTTP and SCC in MCP was depreciated? Again, if this word doesn't make sense, don't worry. We will be covering them in depth in the case. The legacy has been done spec version released in March 2025.
Mayank: So depreciated in March, but the practical turnoff dates vary server by server, so should be fine. Again, just two ways in which we can use our MCP. We will understand both of them in depth. Either they can be running on our machine or they can be hosted on a server. Whenever there is a question for which ChatGPT needs to access MCP, it takes that request to the client. Client hits the server.
Mayank: They talk in the same language. They can tell, server can tell the client what all tools or action it can perform. Then based on that client asks for a particular action and we give the final result to ChatGPT. This is exactly how the approach happens. So this diagram everyone is pretty good to understand this same. So.
Mayank: LLM MCP client, we have the protocol MCP server, which is having tools, prompt and resources. So that is the whole approach. And yes, we will learn that why this support multiple these things, transport layer, this is known as transport layer, how the transport will happen. And this is the complete overall understanding.
Mayank: And one last thing to make it very, very clear, let's try to understand the same flow before and after MCP. Just one more thing to note, everyone, this completely is known as a host, and you can have actually the host, which is your Claude desktop, Claude on the web, any Agentic application, LangChain, LangGraph, Autogen, any of these Agentic framework, Cursor.
Mayank: All of these things also form the part of a host which can have MCP servers or MCP client which can host to a server. I hope this is clear, everyone. What are resources here? We will cover that in depth. Only these two supports. It can support more as well either. As of now, it is there. These two are there. Why they depreciated for coming up with a better one? What challenges with MCP where it can be used and cannot? It can be used with every LLM. Okay.
Mayank: Cool, everyone. Microsoft Copilot, yes. MCP versus Agentic, when to use what? Totally wrong thing. Question. Server should be hosted by us. If we are maintaining the server, then yes. If we are using somewhere else, then no.
Mayank: Many of them are local ones, then it gets hosted on our local, though.
Mayank: Clear? Let's move forward, everyone.
Mayank: There was a slide. I hope I'm audible, everyone.
Mayank: Cool. How are we ensuring that when we use existing MCP server, our data is captured by other dependencies MCPs? We have to see which MCP we are using. Is it sending the data or anything? Okay. Do we need to discuss MCP client first, then need to connect to server? Yes. Ideally, yes. Okay.
Mayank: Let us continue. So now everyone, let us quickly see before and after of MCP, and it will clear out a lot of things. If we think about before and after MCP, let's first discuss about the before scenario. So what exactly happened before? I'm using Gmail API as an example, and you can have an LLM or an agent. So I told you that how we can have any application, Cursor, Claude, or an LLM, ChatGPT, etc.
Mayank: Now, let's talk about the positives, everyone. First, let's quickly talk about the positives. If you have to add a Gmail API, a simple, let's say, Gmail Send API to your LLM or your agent, it's pretty simple. Like, it is very easy to use. If you think about this, super easy to define. You just have to work with a single API, everyone. And yeah, the same will be defined, which you can easily use. Second.
Mayank: Easily understandable. Easily understandable. Why do you say that, Mayank? Because you can go to ChatGPT, or let's say just Gemini only, ask it for a Python script, a Python script which can help me to send email via Gmail.
Mayank: It will give you the complete Python script, everyone, and you can add that as a API in your machine. Okay, so see, it is giving you this script, everyone, which you can just use. Just provide it the client and anything which it wants, do the authorization, and you can use the same. Okay, now let's talk about the negative as well, and that is where it becomes a problematic thing. Talking about the negatives, everyone, the very first thing.
Mayank: You will have duplicate code by everyone or in every project.
Mayank: Every company, every developer would be writing this code up. He will be maintaining the same. If you are having to use the same in 15 projects, you will be writing the same code in 15 projects. Even if you create a centralized repository, then the same will be maintained by thousands of companies, and that is where it becomes a very, very difficult thing.
Mayank: Second, everyone, is that it is redundant. Writing so many code is very, very redundant. We developers, we try to make sure that we follow the principle of drive. That is, do not repeat yourself. Least code thing, okay? And it is prone to failure or change over time, everyone.
Mayank: Google can change few things in its API. Google can mention that, hey, I now need another layer of service. If you are sending the email, give me the subject separately. I now don't support HTML body. I support any other thing. That all thing can also happen. And over time, of course, it will change. It is prone to failure. You can mess up the security. You will need to authorize each and every tool.
Mayank: And, if you think about this, if you think about this, these tools are nothing but just a wrapper.
Mayank: around APIs. So again, overall, it's just a wrapper around API, nothing else. We are having an email send API. We wrap it around and say that, hey, now you are having a tool and our LLM or agent or any application can use it as a function or as a tool. And we have just wrapped it around an API. So all the overheads of maintaining the same is still on us, which is going to be very, very difficult. And these are the major negative. The first one is the main point that it is not scalable.
Mayank: If there are 500 teams, 500 teams will be writing the same code to send their email with their AI services. I hope this thing is clear, everyone. I hope this before part is clear.
Mayank: Before part is clear.
Mayank: Now, let's see the after part, everyone. So, what actually happened after MCP was introduced? So, for the same, a very awesome diagram I will be using. So, pay attention. We are having LLM or agent this time. Now, we are connecting directly via MCP server. So, I actually don't care now.
Mayank: And if I talk about positives, let's quickly understand that MCP server provides me all the tools. I just say to my agent that, hey, and this is generally how, as I mentioned before, that all these things are. So these connectors, I could just go to manage connector. I could just say that, hey, connect with the Gmail one. I could easily connect it. Okay, just let me connect it right in front of you. These are powered by MCP only. Connect, select my email.
Mayank: So it is just connecting. Continue. And just like that, once I do the authorization, my Claude, my application is connecting to the complete Gmail MCP server. I get lots of tools, everyone. In the backend, yes, they will also be calling APIs and everything, but I don't have to maintain or care them. So let's see the same. First, easy to define and access.
Mayank: Is MCP maintain each project or application, or can it be maintained at the MCP company level where we are working for a client? Depends on us. If we are maintaining it, then it can be at any place we want. Still, how is it different from tools? I just showed that. In tools, you were defining and maintaining those things. Here, you are just connecting with.
Mayank: MCP server and you are just mentioning what you want. So complete thing I've just told you. The outcome is the same, but the approach is not totally different. MCP is stateful or stateless. Depends on the kind of an MCP, but majorly they are stateless. Okay. Cool. Will you teach A2A also? Yes. Duplicate part. What if it created as a tool or library? Then how many companies will create their own tool or library? It is still going to be duplicate.
Mayank: project level, you can create a tool or library or at a department level, not at a company level. Okay, cool. If we maintain tools by ourselves, is it like MCP? No, MCP is a protocol, so there is a very much in-depth thing about the protocol part, which is not the case. Okay, can you explain if we maintain tools in our company, why to make MCP servers? The same problem. It is on the left side, right?
Mayank: How the MCP client config done on host? We just mention that what is the client server and we can then connect with it. They can connect with each other. Okay. Many servers can run locally. Can't understand this point. I will explain that when it will come up. So see, STD IO kind of servers are also there, which get startup on your machine.
Mayank: But yes, still, this is a point to consider. Okay. How will I get to know what tools are available? The servers gives you that approach. Why duplicate part is negative. It is negative. No, we have the complete system as developers that, hey, dry, do not repeat yourself. If you're duplicating a code in a code or lots of code, that's a problem. Clear? Shalom. Let's have a break quickly, everyone, then we will come back. So try about 10 minutes.
Mayank: So, I'm not sure if you're aware, but I'm not sure if you're aware.
Mayank: So, I'm going to go ahead and do the same thing for you.
Mayank: I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
Mayank: and it's not. It's not. It's not. It's not.
Mayank: and…
Mayank: So, I'm not sure if you're aware of this, but I'm not sure if you're aware of this.
Mayank: I don't know if you're aware, but I'm not sure if you're aware. I'm not sure if you're aware.
Mayank: I'm going to go to the gate, and I'm going to go to the gate.
Mayank: I'm not sure. I'm not sure. I'm not sure.
Mayank: So, I'm not sure if you're aware of this, but I'm not sure if you're aware of this.
Mayank: for more than what team needs the particular tool. Is MCP an Anthropic product? Do I have to pay.
Mayank: Gmail says that, hey, I am a very big company. Let me create a HTTP-based protocol. Well, good. But then others are not using it. What's the benefit in that? So these were a few of the coaches, everyone.
Mayank: But.
Mayank: So let's start from the beginning.
Mayank: cannot run it. If you ask, send an email to the team about tomorrow's meeting and you ask the model, it can write a complete well-formatted email. It cannot actually send the same email. And that is the entire motivation behind everything in this particular guide. We are a little, I like to say we are a lot lazy, not just a little lazy. We are a lot, lot lazy. In a good way, writing the perfect email isn't the code. Sending it is. We want the model to take the next step too, not just describe it.
Mayank: Though we will be jumping and understanding the same.
Mayank: N.
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah. Hi, Mank. Thanks for the nice explanations. Yeah, a couple of questions I have. Please give me some more time. So how do you differentiate between the protocols between the HCTP and the streamable HCTP? Are you going to come up later on or?
Mayank: Yes, we will be covering it.
Jitendra Biswal: More details, right?
Mayank: Yeah, yeah, properly detailed, I will show you.
Mayank: So it should be fine.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, and can the MCP server that, can it be extendable, let's say, because Google MCP server that they have given, so can I, you know, extend that Google MCP server through an extension method, or maybe, like, you know, derivations, like, you know, inheritance kind of, like, process?
Mayank: Have an MCP server call another MCP server. OK.
Jitendra Biswal: Like,
Mayank: It is not extendable. It's not a code. You can have an MCP server which is having another MCP server inside it.
Jitendra Biswal: Wrapper, like a wrapper, like…
Mayank: Not wrapper, not wrapper. MCP, it will be a resource. So an MCP just have resource. So if I show you the diagram, one minute, where is Zoom? Zoom pagya. Okay, am I sharing the screen? Sorry.
Jitendra Biswal: Nay.
Mayank: Sorry. So it actually got into that small thing. See, MCP just have these things.
Mayank: Ideally, you can have a MCP server, but in a programming sense, which you are saying, it is not possible. You are extending it or anything. No, it doesn't work like that.
Jitendra Biswal: Yeah, because we are using a, you know, on the GitHub MCP server, and we found that it is not equipped with a lot of tools. So we have to go for creating our own MCP server. So that's the reason I'm saying, because it is a waste of, you know, effort for us, because GitHub is a well-known tool that should have all the tools, I mean, what we're looking for.
Mayank: No, that is not normally how it happens. GitHub is doing all these things for a reason. Just what I meant is that you can have a MCP server trigger, let's say.
Jitendra Biswal: Mmhm.
Mayank: And inside this, I have not checked this with the code, but you can have another MCP, sorry, MCP client tool. So you can have it like this. So this server, it is having another MCP client inside it. This client can now again connect with some other MCP. So you can give it the endpoint where you want it to connect and other things as well. So this is what is possible. If you tell that, Hey, this is your MCP.
Mayank: GitHub client. Now, when the request comes in here for GitHub, it can go to this one. It will close it out. It will go back.
Mayank: But at the same time, this is not what we do a lot. It is possible, but not something which we do a lot.
Jitendra Biswal: No, no, I didn't get it. So are you going to have multiple clients or because let's say whatever the GitHub MCP server is given by published by the GitHub. So we should have a generic client, MCP client in our VS Code.
Mayank: So, I told you that VS Code acts as a host and is having internally the client. You cannot see that as of now here. You cannot see it like this, the way I show you here.
Jitendra Biswal: So, what I understand, like, you know, I can utilize the MCP server to give it my GitHub. Also, if I see that some of the tools are not exist, I can get another MCP server and host it. And the client can… So, how the client will know intelligently to call to which MCP server?
Mayank: It gets the tool, client, when it gets connected to the MCP server, it gets.
Jitendra Biswal: No, no, it will get tools. It will get tools, but again, we should call to the… because all the doc index are there in the tools, not in the…
Mayank: It did not just get the tools, it gets the information as well. You give it a proper description. You give it the input schema.
Mayank: This is just what your client gets. If you do subtract two numbers here, it will call add without the break. So the client, just like a server client architecture, client gets that, hey, these are the tools. This is the input schema.
Mayank: This is what I have to send, this is the output which.
Mayank: These are the required one. Exactly. I'm showing you right in front of you that what exactly it gets. So the more you can make it descriptive, the more better it'll be. That is the case just.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, okay.
Jitendra Biswal: Multiple entries, same name. Can there be a scope of name conflict can happen? So how it'll handle MCP server?
Mayank: But again, description is there. It can happen if you try to make it happen, but otherwise normally it doesn't happen. It will either ask you, so it is based on now again how you are maintaining your host and server, host and client. It will either ask you just like Claude asked you, but otherwise if you know that the name collision might happen, just make the description better.
Mayank: Or give your host, so whenever you are using your Claude or VS Code, just mention properly. So I could mention to my VS Code that use LangChain MCP so that I'm helping it out. So normal thing here as well. But normally it doesn't happen. We are fine. We have a well-defined MCPs which are very much properly having in-depth descriptions. So that all is pretty good.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay. My last question is, MCP is hosted as a server, as a server, right? In the, let's say, the app service or whatever, any of the service, web service it run. How it is run? Is it run as a Docker container or if you don't do the Dockerize, how is it run?
Mayank: Just like any other service, it depends. If you wanted to have a Docker container, it can run as a Docker container. If you're running it with fast MCP just as a normal server or an API server starts.
Mayank: So just as a simple server, which can take a request, nothing else. If you want it to be a Docker container, you can have a Docker container. If you want it to be having with ECS and other things, it can have that as well. Just how you start a server in different, different ways.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, but we… but you need AJIT web server to… to have a JASON, and type of, certificate.
Mayank: It's two members.
Jitendra Biswal: Streamable HTTP protocol or type of protocol.
Mayank: Not streamable always. As I told, there are two protocols, so either we can have… Emulation.
Jitendra Biswal: HDDIO and Streamable, let's say. So if you want to have a local, then HDD.
Mayank: Not local like that. So Notion, Gmail, they can ask that, hey, I will start up an MCP local server on your end. This local server will make the request to me on my server, on my APIs or tools. So again, when I will cover, I think it will be clear.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay, okay, that's all. I just want to know the.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: I never knew you, K.
Mayank: That's what I.
Jitendra Biswal: Okay. Okay. And, can you just share us these? Because, you know, the architecture level, like, you know, certifications, for the AI, can you give the list so that we can focus on those? Because that's the, because I'm a bit experienced persons, so I look for the architecture level type of role. I like to focus more.
Mayank: So, these things will help, you know, but the way in depth we are covering.
Jitendra Biswal: No, no, I'm going fine, but as a certificate responsible, I need to show something as a, you know, this is my patch.
Mayank: I will not be able to provide the certificate.
Jitendra Biswal: Not you.
Jitendra Biswal: Not you, I'm dealing with for Microsoft or maybe, you know, open AI, the certifications that.
Mayank: So in that, what happened is that whatever I'm teaching you, there is Claude certification as well, and which you can go and actually the same concept is there. Nothing else is there. If you go in here, they will be asking you for MCP. Once you know this much in depth MCP, it will be pretty much the same thing. If I go on, let's say Claude Associate or Developer one.
Mayank: These are the things which they ask, nothing else. In the staples, they are having MCP. MCP, you will see the both staples is the same only.
Mayank: Concept, I can teach. I cannot guide my teaching to a certificate. Normally, I would never do that.
Jitendra Biswal: No, no, we'll.
Jitendra Biswal: We do digestion because that can be marketed.
Mayank: Yeah.
Jitendra Biswal: Because now the market niche, okay, they're asking you…
Mayank: D d d.
Mayank: Let's relate to the doubts because many people are waiting.
Jitendra Biswal: Thank you.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Yeah. Hi. Hi, Mike.
Mayank: Hi there, JTS. Hey.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: So, two questions. One is, if I build some MCP server, using any, fast MCP, through VS Code, okay? And then, if I want, okay.
Mayank: You can invite.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: If I want that, if I want that, MCP to be connected with Cloud Desktop, is that connectivity possible?
Mayank: Yes, it is.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: It is possible. Okay. And my second doubt is, for example, if I am using Google Vertex AI, you, are quite expert in GCP, so in Vertex AI also, can we build the MCP, or to build the MCP, I need to use some other service to deploy, for example, Cloud Run or GKE, something like that.
Mayank: Again, Vertex AI is a separate application. It is majorly for your AI part and everything. For building an MCP, you will just choose a machine, a simple VPS machine or something where you will host it just like API.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, and even I can deploy in the Cloud Run as well, right?
Mayank: Oh, those all things are the same, exactly the way we handle anything in the area.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay. And once I deploy this, actually, maybe they will give me a API link, which has to be used to access any kind of tools under that MCP, right?
Mayank: You will get a MCP server link, just like how… if I show you…
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: You get it, 127.001.
Mayank: We will be pushing our MCP like I plan to show you how, I hope it works. I hope they have not changed this thing. I plan to show you how you can push your MCP servers to PYPI and then anyone across us can also use it. So that would be your part as well, how you will be with me creating an MCP server live and pushing it so that everyone can use it. And yeah, I think that's the highest level of understanding. If you sit in an interview and tell that I have created an MCP server, that is the level of depth I want.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, sure. Thank you so much. And just to reconfirm, that this first MCP that we are using, we can deploy anywhere, maybe in a compute machine, maybe in Cloud Run, wherever, which is giving the runtime.
Mayank: Just a normal.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Yeah, yeah.
Mayank: Exactly, exactly, exactly. So don't do a problem.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Thank you so much.
krishnakumar: Hi, Mayank. Kr.
Mayank: Hi Kish, please.
krishnakumar: Yeah, quick, quick, quick, quick one only, not too much, like in.
krishnakumar: Can you show me, like, what all the tools are there in the… and that's below the servers? I'm.
Mayank: One minute. You want to see these tools?
krishnakumar: No, no, under the MCP server.
Mayank: Okay, so if I show you MCP resources, so it is saying LangChain, Yahapi LangChain skill, define tools, invoke with context, this, let me show you in BS code somehow, MCP, list servers, docs by LangChain, it is running.
Mayank: Restart server. Show configuration. Show output. Configure model access. Set the model server that can be used by MCP sapling. Browse resources.
Mayank: Actually, you know, it is available in here. It is telling that what audit is having if you focus a little bit. Let me show you this in our empty viewer. This is like the complete resource file which we are getting. See, it is telling when to use and everything, quick reference and everything. Yeah, RPA model identifiers, common kwachas, verification checklist.
Mayank: No, this is not the one. Just one minute. I can show you. Okay, one minute. Actually, we can ask directly. That's also works. What I can do is we can go to view.
Mayank: Chat. Chat. Close. Use a LangChain speed. Tell me what all tools.
Mayank: and resources it has.
Mayank: So, it will be the same which I showed you in this, see?
krishnakumar: Okay.
Mayank: Search docs by LangChain. Search LangChain documentation and examples. Query docs file system docs by LangChain. Read or search the virtual documentation file system using commands such as cat, head, rg, and tree. Submit feedback. Report incorrectly, outdated, incomplete, or broken LangChain documentation. These are the tools.
Mayank: These are the other resources. It's a documentation MCP, so it helps retrieve current language and knowledge. It does not itself execute create agent, call an LLM, run your tools, or access your application data. So it just gives you the documentation.
krishnakumar: Okay. Okay, Mani, thank you. Thank you.
Mayank: So a better way of just seeing this ideally, I think there will be Lang chain, sorry, MCP visualizer maybe somewhere MCP inspector.
Mayank: There are multiple ways. You can, the best way is just to add it in the GitHub, add it in the cloud as well. You can just manage connectors. You can see, it will give you the tools and everything. I forget how you can see the same, but you can do it via code as well, but the backend with our code is only running.
krishnakumar: Okay. Thank you, Molly.
Mayank: Thank you.
Vasudev N: Hi, Mayank, good morning.
Mayank: Divya, you'.
Vasudev N: So, Mayank, you have created this MCP, the local MCP which you have created today. Is it possible to include it to VS Code, like how you have added for the LangChain?
Mayank: Yes, it should be. Let me try it in front of you. It is. I know it is, but just that I don't use VS Code a lot, but let me still do that. VS Code chat server is going run this MCP server so I can access it inside you. But it's very straightforward.
Mayank: I think I can get it by adding it, but like…
Vasudev N: Okay, why I'm asking because let's say I have Swagger APIs I have 100 more than 100 applications and I have Swagger APIs which I want to create an MCP and I want to give that MCP to our internal team only I don't want to expose so like in the VS Code if I connect that one and if I can able to like my entire team can able to access that MCP server that could be helpful instead of exposing to.
Vasudev N: That's the reason I'm just asking. So how we can…
Mayank: It's possible. It is possible. Let me try to run it. Forget how to just do that. I've done this.
Vasudev N: Otherwise, we can do in Nest Plus, no problem, man. So, just…
Mayank: Just give me a minute, I think it will be possible. Sure.
Mayank: Motherboard is very easy. Let's start. I think it has been six, seven months since I used VS Code chat. I want to access this locally running MCP server in my VS Code chat. So earlier I used to maintain all these things.
Vasudev N: Even VS Code is not possible, right? Is it possible to include it in cloud?
Mayank: It is everywhere. It is possible everywhere, not a problem. But if it happens, it is not a problem at all. It is generally possible everywhere. That's the benefit of MCP.
Mayank: Let us see this in VS Code as well.
Vasudev N: Okay.
Mayank: It is running. MCP service working. The important detail is STTI, so you normally do not keep this running outside. VS Code should launch that command and communicate inside your MCP create. It will need these things. This is something which we need. Yeah. This is something which, yes, it will have to need. So yeah, let us do one thing. Let us go to VS Code. MCP add server.
Mayank: SQDIO server is also one thing. Add the command.
Mayank: Okay, one minute. I will have to ask it. Can you give me the command and let me paste it? It is like this. Let me do it. It will take a minute. So I think everyone else will also learn with it. So.
Mayank: Actually, the command will be uv run python server dot py. This is the command, uv run python server dot py.
Vasudev N: Okay.
Mayank: So see, enter this, but make sure VS code is using this folder as the working directory. So this will be the command as I mentioned, my local server. I hope the working directory is also fine.
Mayank: Let me make it available in just this workspace, not globally. Let's see. So my local server, stdio uv run python serves dot py. This is actually how you add it. I have to showcase that actually. As of now, I've not shown it. And this CWD is something which we will have to also fix up. So we should fix it up, actually. We should fix it up. So in that case, what happened is that my VS Code, in a way, it knows that, hey, this is where your.
Mayank: service list this is exactly where your server lives and I could just now make sure so this is created now vs code MCP JSON now I could start a new chat maybe and check do you can you start.
Mayank: Warm up. Okay, it's still there now. Running. So see, now the same is running. It is having tools. It is running. Can you access warm up server?
Mayank: So, I will be… I will give you a recording, maybe, Teja.
Vasudev N: Cheers.
Mayank: I can see the form of configuration, but I can't directly connect or invoke it from here. You can test it in VS Code by starting the MCP server or running. Okay, one minute. Show output. Let me open, let me see MCP in motion. Let me fix it up.
Vasudev N: So.
Mayank: You just run it from here, and it can be accessible anywhere in the world, like, that's the idea. Anywhere in your machine as of now, once you make it active, anywhere in the world.
Vasudev N: Okay. And that, link, or, we can give this server link to access, throughout our team, right, Mayank? Yeah.
Vasudev N: Okay, so they can…
Mayank: Either you will have to create a GitHub repo or you will have to create, you will have to host it, but I will show you how you can share it.
Vasudev N: Sure, sure, sure.
Mayank: In your team, then everyone can use it. You can just give them a link, they can add that configuration, just like how we are adding it here, right?
Mayank: They can add it, and then you can use it, not a problem at all. Not even a single IOTA of.
Vasudev N: And my last question, Mayank, regarding tools and resource, you mentioned, right? Like.
Mayank: Mmh.
Vasudev N: 99%, we have to use tools only, but when.
Vasudev N: I think like this AP, if I say this Swagger APS, better to use tools or resource?
Mayank: Tools. Your Swagger APIs are just tools only, nothing else.
Vasudev N: Okay, okay. Federated, that's all.
Mayank: It's.
Vasudev N: That's all. Thank you so much.
Mayank: Thank you. Anju.
Anshul: Yeah, unmute.
Mayank: Hi.
Anshul: Okay. So first question is, so I'm just bringing it from what we had learned earlier. So earlier, we used to define tool as a function. We used to bind it to an agent, create agent, and then change. And then when you used to invoke the agent, then the tool schema in the background is passed to the LLM, and then that's how LLM decides what tool to call, right?
Anshul: Versus in MCP, for example, when we create an MCP server, for example, when we integrate, let's say, Google or Gmail MCP server to our application, and let's say this MCP server has 50 tools in it, for example.
Anshul: Now, when we connect that MCP server, then you refer to another JSON protocol, you know, through which that entire tool data from MCP server comes and sits in the client, correct? Is that correct understanding till now?
Mayank: I will explain what happens, that would be much easier to understand.
Anshul: So, so, okay, let, let, let me just complete what I'm.
Mayank: Yeah, sure.
Anshul: So at high level, that entire tool information in JSON, that new JSON format sits in my client. And let's say when I create agent in LenkChain, then that tool list is binded to my agent. Now, when I invoke the agent, is that entire tool list sent to my LLM to further take an action? Or how does that work, Amir?
Mayank: So that I've already explained. Two things are coming up here, I will make it clear. See?
Mayank: yeah, let me explain it somewhere here. Well, let me see how I put here. See, you have an agent, okay? Now you can give your agent tools and to your agent only, you can give an MCP server as well. Okay?
Mayank: Now, when your agent kind of starts, it is totally on how you are defining it. Either it can load all the tools, it can load all the servers and everything. But again, when you send it a request.
Mayank: And we have discussed in middleware that how we can have just relevant tools and everything loaded, but let's take the call that everything is getting loaded. Then your agent can understand that, okay, if it's a Gmail MCP server and you ask it to send a Gmail, send an email, it'll reach out to the MCP server, tell that what it wants, then it'll search, it'll get all the tools, how they work and everything. So for example.
Mayank: In our use case, when the agent will try to access, it will try to get that, hey, it is having greet and add. These were the two tools we have created. It knows the description. Now it is just like a normal tool calling. So it can send that complete thing. Just it will give that to client. So what, how it will happen is that agent will notice that, hey, there is a request. Seems like we have an MCP server. Agent will ask MCP client to connect with the server and get all the tools which it knows. MCP client will go to the server.
Mayank: get the tools, send it back to the agent. Agent will then see that, okay, it is having a send email tool inside it. It needs this, this, this from me. Let me send all of them and send another request. It will send to the MCP client that, hey, this time, call this tool. This time, make sure that you're calling the tool. Once you call the tool, MCP server will call the tool with all the right arguments, and it will just work in this manner.
Mayank: just that MCP client is coming in between. Otherwise, it is just connection of hosts, nothing else, and that is because of our protocol.
Anshul: Yeah, so in the first, so when the first time LLM calls the MCP server.
Mayank: Oh.
Anshul: It's gonna send back the entire tool list.
Mayank: Yes, yes, you get all the list tools, yeah.
Anshul: Yeah, and then LLM is going to reason over the tool list, and then specifically ask, okay, send me… I want to use this tool for doing the next section, right?
Mayank: Exactly, exactly.
Anshul: Okay, and so, so, the entire tool list, we're gonna add to my, context and the token.
Mayank: Yes.
Anshul: Tuesday.
Mayank: Yes, yes, yes, exactly. Much for it.
Anshul: Yeah, for example, if let's say Gmail or any other MCP server has, let's say, 52, so it's going to send the entire 52 data to the LLM, and then LLM is going to reason over it, right?
Mayank: Yes, exactly. All the understanding is correct.
Anshul: Okay.
Mayank: Just, of course, we can have an approach via which we can easily control that, hey, let's not have all of them. Let's try to just have some of them. That is also possible. Let's not actually load all the MCP servers and everything. So, majorly, what you're thinking is right. That's optimization, but otherwise, it's the same process.
Nitin Gupta: Mike, just to interrupt here, like, in the continuation of the previous question, what Anshu was asking, I think we should select the tools, right? Because otherwise, it will make it heavier, no?
Mayank: But how will you know.
Nitin Gupta: Okay.
Nitin Gupta: It will load all the tools.
Mayank: But how will you know without request? How will you know without seeing the request that which tool you have to load? I'm showing you the right thing in front of you. See, I sent a hi. It is giving me some questions. Let me show context. See, it sent a very simple system prompt. Custom tools, 18K. Custom agents, 869K. Skills, 2K. Messages.
Mayank: 18.4K. So just in a single hi, it has sent custom system tools, which is 18.1K. I'm using Haiku. I think if I use model and okay, sorry.
Mayank: You have to switch model. So I'm just showing you, you cannot have that. Sonnet and others can actually make that call. They will not. And again, I think we have seen this in the middle where we have seen that. How can we load just the required tools? But we cannot do that from the get start, right? Because it is not possible. How will you know that I want to send an email or read an email? I hope I'm making sense.
Mayank: So there are just two MCP connected servers. That is why it is not crying that much. Okay, but this is just context seven, so I have to add more servers here. Pretty strange. I think I had more servers, but should be fine. But how? Actually, now it depends on how many MCPs are being sent and how you are configuring it. But if you are having 10 MCP servers connected, your.
Mayank: First message will send and list the tools from all those MCP servers. That is how it happens. Okay?
Nitin Gupta: Mmhm.
Mayank: Because how will it make a call? You don't have call send message in the first message. So that is why it happens. And that is why the context grows that much with the first message. So I hope it is.
Nitin Gupta: Thank you.
Anshul: Okay, so Matt, is there any way, I mean, to the similar question, is there any way we can do some sort of a semantic sort.
Mayank: Better beer. Better beers.
Anshul: Oh, no.
Mayank: Yeah, we.
Anshul: Okay.
Mayank: Where's.
Anshul: Yeah, when we're calling MCP server for the first time to get the tool list, whatever functions tools it had, so can we intercept there itself and ask the MCP server to send me only relevant tools? I mean, is there anything?
Mayank: I think you should be able to do it when the client sends it to the host. So when the MCP client sends it, because server, we are not controlling. Server will give what it wants. Via middleware, you should be able to control, and rather not via middleware, actually, on the client end, you should be able to control what your model is getting. So middleware, maybe we can control that. Runtime and everything will be clear. We can control that, not a problem. Middleware is the way.
Anshul: So there's a way we can probably filter out. Instead of sending all the tool lists from MCP server to the LLM, we can intercept and we can decide what are tools I should send to my LLM, right?
Mayank: Exactly. You can do that. Just exactly how I showed you in the prebuilt middleware. There was a LLM tool selector where you can reduce it. Middleware is the way of doing it. You will have to cut the outcome in the middle, right? So that is how it is possible. Let me see if they have it in the documentation. Maybe tool interceptors. They got excessive runtime, runtime with over here, custom interceptors, progress, notification, elicitation.
Mayank: I have not covered it. I just moved it last night. I will add it again. It is possible to answer your question. Yes, it is possible. Claude after Sonnet version does that. So by default, Claude Haiku doesn't do it. I'm not sure if they have changed it in the latest version, but from Sonnet onwards, it actually does that.
Mayank: Yep.
Anshul: My second question might be, so…
Anshul: In the MCP server, we discussed the three components, which are the tools, resources, and prompts, right?
Mayank: Yep.
Anshul: So tools, we understand what tools are. So resources and prompts. So is it right understanding, let's say when we define a tool, then, I mean, when the tool is binded to, let's say, create AJIT in LangChain, then it actually sends the tool schema to the LLM, right? So is resources that tool schema, number one? And number two, when we say prompt, so when we define our tools, when we write these doc strings, these.
Mayank: It is not, it is not the tool schema. It is.
Anshul: It's not that. It's not that. Okay.
Mayank: No.
Anshul: So then, when we're going to identify it going forward, you want to explain how you do that? Okay.
Mayank: I will explain that, I will explain that.
Anshul: And just last thing, man. So since I'm a non-coder, frankly, so I mean, I understand this concept. Can in some session, can you just give a quick demo in whatever session you would like to decide, how we can create a normal API using Swagger, just a normal API using Swagger?
Mayank: I will either give the recording, or Swagger, I will show via FastAPI. Swagger page we get via FastAPI. Swagger is normally kind of used in Java majorly.
Anshul: Okay, okay. So, since I've heard about it, so I use it, but using it… I mean, how do you create a normal API endpoint? Just that, just that.
Mayank: So we'll do that. I will showcase that. It's very simple in the way, so it should not.
Anshul: Oh, great. Thank you. That's it.
Mayank: Okay, cool. If you're from non tech background, just try to make sure that you do revision properly because things will get a lot taken as you move forward in course. Yeah.
dipika vijapur: Hi.
Mayank: My.
Mayank: Akanksha, you were next. It wasn't you, right? Yeah, Akanks.
akanksha Verma: Mike, the first question is, like, where is the possibility of you answering the question? Is, like, should I put in chat or Q&A? Chat. Chat. Okay. The second thing…
Mayank: Yeah.
Mayank: Sorry, if your question is not getting answered, there can be two ways, two reasons. First, it is not relevant to what I'm teaching or it is something which I have kind of explained multiple times. Second, which normally doesn't happen a lot.
Mayank: is understanding this. If we can work out some other better way, I'm happy to then do that. But as of now, this is the approach which we are following. It's not a complaint, so it's fine. And the second thing is like, I understand the concepts and whenever you give the assignments, right, I do it looking at the launching documents and your files, right, whichever you provide, like the middleware and everything. But after two, three weeks, if someone asks me to write that code, I'll not be able to do that. So is it okay that?
akanksha Verma: Well, it's not a complaint, so it'.
Mayank: Yep.
akanksha Verma: And the second thing is like, I understand the concepts and whenever you give the assignments, right, I do it looking at the launching documents and your files, right, whichever you provide, like the middleware and everything. But after two, three weeks, if someone asked me to write that code, I'll not be able to know that. So is it okay that?
akanksha Verma: Okay, totally, yeah. And the third thing is, like, the MCP thing, right? When you were showing that MCP inspector thing, right, it was telling that it is, sending, client… MCP server was sending it to clients, the tools, the prompts, and the resources. Isn't… shouldn't it be the other way?
Mayank: It is right, madhub. I will showcase it. So, see, when your client starts, when your client starts, client only here.
akanksha Verma: Mmhm.
Mayank: It actually reaches out to all the MCP servers. It actually does this thing, ki bhai, tell me quickly what all you are having. Kyunki dapi yaar, client koi nahpi banda.
Mayank: Needs to fill this up. So even when Claude Desktop starts, it reaches out to every MCP that, hey, tell me what all tools you have and everything so that I can show it in my UI. So client is sending this request to the server. Then server returns up with something. So client send a request that, hey, give me all the tools you have, list all the tools. Then response was this, which you receive from server.
akanksha Verma: So it has both, like, the parameters going and the response coming back from the MCP server, right?
Mayank: Yes, it is that only just that it is not rest based. It is JSON RPC two based, which I will explain what it is and why it was like that and might also benefit.
akanksha Verma: Yeah, okay. Okay, that's all. Thank you.
Mayank: Okay, thank you. Cool, one minute. Akansha is done. Next is Mitesh.
Mayank: Then I think Nitin then dipika, then.
Mayank: Goodbye.
Mitesh: Mank, I hope I'm audible.
Mayank: cases you ought to be.
Mitesh: Yeah, sorry, I missed in between a little bit. So when I see host, it might be very stupid question at this point of time, but host versus client, right? When I say host, it's like a container where it would just delegate it to client to decide what to call, when to call, right?
Mayank: Again, I will explain it with an analogy first, and then otherwise.
Mayank: See, if you have a mobile, just with a mobile, you cannot connect to your network.
Mitesh: Right.
Mayank: Okay, you need to make sure that you add a SIM in a sense that SIM is a host. Similarly, Claude as an application or VS Code as an application directly does not connect to MCP servers. VS Code has been there before MCP as well. So VS Code doesn't go directly and say to MCP server, this is what I want. VS Code starts an MCP client. We can create our own client internally to showcase the client in this application is difficult. I will try if I can showcase that to you in the next time.
Mayank: But VS Code starts a client and say that, hey, you have to communicate with this particular MCP server. You tell me what tools it is having. I will tell you to connect with it. MCP server and client speak the same language, which is MCP protocol language or JSON or IPC.
Mitesh: So your SIM card is your client, right?
Mayank: SIM card is your client, yes.
Mitesh: So, your phone tells us…
Mayank: This number, mobile phone is your host, and network is your server.
Mitesh: Works. The second question that I have is because before this few in few of the doubts, the question or the idea that came in is MCP server aggregator can be created for a company. Like example, we have a very restricted environment that all other things cannot be processed, called, et cetera, right? So an MCP server aggregator can be created which will call the MCP servers, let's say Gmail MCP server, right? That can be created or how it can be handled?
Mayank: For our own servers, we try to, for our own application, we can create MCP servers. That's the best way. So, if you want to use it with, if you want to give the access to normal people or to AI clients.
Mayank: For servers which are already available for this application, we use them. Maybe we can wrap around it just like I showed you to do a little bit of more keeping on. We can create our own servers on top of that as well. Like it is just generally like an API server, just.
Mitesh: Exactly.
Mayank: MCP nothing else.
Mitesh: And, again, I'm just reconfirming it, because.
Mayank: Boom.
Mitesh: I'm a little confused on this.
Mayank: Noise.
Mitesh: MCP server or tools can have a RBAC assigned so that a particular thing is like using the node based middlewares, we can restrict them, right? This person can use this MCP server and tool or this person cannot use this, this login, right?
Mayank: Hamilton.
Mitesh: Panik is correct?
Mayank: We have authentication, the same as authenticated. Then after that, for a separate tools, authentication at a tool level.
Mayank: Normally, we authenticate the complete server.
Mayank: Normally, you authenticate the complete server. Once the same has been authenticated, we say that, okay, now later we use the same.
Mitesh: No, but if I suppose example I for a developer, I want to give them a read and write access to the GitHub company GitHub, right? But to let's say the product manager, I just want to give them a read access. So I have to authenticate the MCP server completely, but the tools has to be restricted, right? In that case.
Mayank: Hmm. So in that ways, in that ways, just gimme a second. Can we restrict the tool based on auth? That is the question. Let me.
Mayank: check it if it is possible in the latest one I have not written it ever in an MCP server can we restrict tools based on auth I think it should be possible but let's see.
Mitesh: I will try. I will try.
Mayank: It is possible. It is possible. From a coding mindset, I can understand. Like, even if MCP doesn't support it, I can understand how it might be possible.
Mayank: Because I know the code, how it is written, right.
Mitesh: Yeah, that's what I was saying, node based middleware at the ad before.
Mayank: It is.
Mitesh: I can do that.
Mayank: Yes, it is possible. Although I'm not able to, like, again, ChatGPT has given a lot better quick answer, but it is possible. Should not be a problem because what happened is that, we mentioned or we said back that, hey, which tools are available? Okay. So when we send that back, we can check with authentication, like what level of access the person is having. So it's a simple if code. That's why I know that coding wise, it should be possible at least.
Mitesh: Yeah, perfect. Thank you. I have two more questions. I will take it fast. There is a tool runtime, right? Do we have anything on the MCP server side where I can get the details like a tool runtime state or context and use it? Or it is the three things that you talked about, right? The tools, the resources and that part.
Mitesh: Okay.
Mayank: First, not sync it up. Tool runtime is a LangChain thing. MCP is a standalone prot.
Mitesh: OK, got it. So two different things. The last one.
Mayank: Thank you.
Mitesh: Is, last question.
Mayank: That said, just one thing, sorry.
Mitesh: Yes.
Mayank: Just one thing.
Mayank: LangChain does support, and rather it should support, as we were able to see in its documentation, that LangChain says that, hey, MCP servers run a separate process, they can't access LangChain runtime information. Interceptors can bridge this gap by giving you access to the runtime because, of course, runtime will be a much helpful thing.
Mayank: So LangChain does support where MCP servers can access the runtime of the user in the request. Ideally, yes, it will be sending the request runtime in the request. So makes a lot of sense. So in that way, your MCP servers via LangChain can access its runtime to give you a much better answer.
Mitesh: No.
Mayank: Yeah, but by default, it's a different concept.
Mitesh: It's basically interceptors are kind of a middleware of line chat. Simple.
Mayank: Kind of, yeah, you can mention that, hey, MCP interceptors helps you to send that information so that your MCP is having a little bit more idea.
Mitesh: More ideas.
Mayank: So we just need to get the context. Multi server MCP client, it is having multiple servers, pool interceptors, just inject this user context, whatever we have created. So just to make sure that we are having a good idea around that.
Mitesh: I think so we will cover this next week, I think.
Mayank: There's two next… two next.
Mitesh: Okay, got it.
Mayank: Not week, next to next week.
Mitesh: Got it. Last question is not related to, right now, AI agents, and this, LangChain bot. I'm, I'm searching for something on, web where I can do coding. I don't know, I don't, I can't use it on my, company lapt.
Mitesh: So, can you suggest something on this? Which, like, I heard about MASH API and other things, but do you have anything, any setup which I can use it for a remote work with some paid subscription?
Mayank: You can use Collab, you know, what coding you want to do.
Mitesh: But agents, AI agents.
Mayank: Ai agents, and what in AI agents?
Mitesh: Basically, I'm planning to… my end goal would be to use Snowflake's data to create a chat agent for the executive committee.
Mayank: Can you… do you have access to a machine?
Mitesh: I have, which is very low, I3, but would not run, it'll crash.
Mayank: Umm.
Mayank: Okay. You want to run an agent, right?
Mitesh: Mmhm.
Mayank: Actually, all of these things they are having, like LangChain is also having its LangChain, I think, hosted one. So, but you need to do that. Can you check out maybe CrewAI once as well? CrewAI is also having…
Mayank: It's server.
Mayank: Where you can host it directly, but in the enterprise side, it lets you create the same.
Mitesh: Got it. Got it.
Mitesh: Strange.
Mayank: out once, anytime crew, these are having it, but where you can write the code. So it is having the studio. They run on their machine.
Mitesh: Perfect.
Mayank: So that is something because mesh API is not that mesh API is a separate thing.
Mitesh: Yeah, no, I'm just talking on my ship here because wherever I can get a VS code inbuilt in that particular login, it would be great for me.
Mayank: It's a VS Code type, right? VS Code type. It is provided in AWS also. It is provided VS Code server or something might be there.
Mitesh: Someone was saying something, but I forgot that name. Let me go back.
Mayank: Huh, just check it once. Mesh API is a separate thing. Mesh API also is an.
Mitesh: It's like a…
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: It is an API gateway, nothing else. On the plus, it is not… like, it is by AI Festa, which is by, I think, Dhuvnarati Thoitana Tho. It is not very big in that name. So, but it.
Mitesh: Perfect.
Mayank: API gateway, not that.
Mitesh: Perfect. Last question. You and Paul would be having any offline sessions in Bangalore?
Mayank: We meet every week, but sessions only.
Mitesh: Just for learning it and for us to be.
Mayank: Highly difficult. I, I do take sessions for companies, corporate trainings, but when…
Mitesh: I will reach out to you for that.
Mayank: when we meet, if you reach out to me for corporate training, reach out on this email id. My team handles it, so it will be able to reach out much quickly. Okay, so as of now, there is no plan. If it changes, we'll let you know for sure.
Mayank: Hello?
dipika vijapur: Hello?
Mayank: Hello, yes, hi Divya.
dipika vijapur: Hi, Mayak. Good morning. I have a small doubt regarding the host and the MCP client. Not able to understand it correctly. So, what is exactly the host and what is the client? Because the example that you showed, there was nothing specific, like, we wrote anything about client in that. There was one host application, and through that only we connected it. So, I'm somehow not able to connect those dots. Can you please…
Mayank: Yes, sure, sure, sure, sure. See, actually what happened is that VS Code internally starts its own host, so you cannot see it like this. The analogy which I gave you that mobile SIM is the best analogy to understand it, but to still make it clear what I can show you, we can create fast MCP host, sorry, create a client.
Mayank: Fast MCP client. Yes, we can create a server and a client like this. I cannot, I think I cannot show you that like this. Let me still try it up if I can show you the host.
dipika vijapur: No, you can just tell me what exactly happened in the backend. We wrote one application, right? Abhi hamne ak application likha. Toh usne, uske paas toh client hai nahi. Toh usne peto server ko kaise kanek kya.
Mayank: No, no, no, no, it is having the client. It is having the application.
dipika vijapur: Johamnik Lasky.
Mayank: This is an MCP client. This is an MCP client.
dipika vijapur: The inspector is the client?
Mayank: Yes, if I do a request, pay attention. Five, nine, execute tool. See, client to server, a call got made.
dipika vijapur: Okay, this is the inspector which is running on our client, right? Can you go to the code?
Mayank: Fine.
dipika vijapur: Ha. So, Ismih Hamnesepek Sar.
Mayank: Yes.
dipika vijapur: My dog.
dipika vijapur: Okay.
Mayank: No, no, no, no.
dipika vijapur: So, the inspector acted as a client, is that what you're saying?
dipika vijapur: So, it just connected, this is… then which is my host application?
Mayank: Host or client? In this, it is just the client and the server host. They are able to connect and everything. In VS Code and Claude, your host is VS Code and Claude. They start up a separate client underneath them, which can connect to them, which I will show you. Like every client gets started and everything.
Mayank: But it is internal, it is not like that. So when I added this docs LangChain to MCP client start internally, because it supports this thing, it supports this, you can add a server and everything.
dipika vijapur: Hmm.
Mayank: And because it supports this thing called MCP Client Language Connection Manalia.
dipika vijapur: Right, right.
Mayank: Post ko pata hai, ki mere piche MCP ki client chalra hai hai, gin ko mai reach out kar sakta hai. Ek client mai nagche se connected hai, ek mai notion.
Mayank: request, it will be able to make sense of that. These three are running.
Mayank: I can stop any if I want. So I can stop it. Now this is not running. So in a way, you don't see that thing is hided. If you think about this, if you think about it, the connection will help. So yes, that is how it is helping. I will get, actually I forget that I will try to get the IDs of those clients somehow so we can understand whether they will be having some IDs.
dipika vijapur: I have an idea, I was just a little confused kykh nahinja code lika usmhy kya hoste or.
Mayank: Code means nothing. Code means there is no client or no host. Code is just a server. This is a server which anyone can access, nothing else.
dipika vijapur: exactly did we do again in terms of host and CL this is a little confusing for me I will I will tell you I will tell you I will tell you let's say Claude okay now I can ask Claude the.
Mayank: I will, I will tell you, I will tell you, I will tell you. Okay. May pass application and let's say cloud. Okay.
Mayank: Now, I can ask Claude the questions regarding LangChain, it can give me the answer, but then you can never be sure the answer is always right, because it is not the needed information, right?
dipika vijapur: Perfect, yes.
Mayank: Okay, maybe it'll learn that and it will not be accessing it every time. Web search, maybe also you can get the stale results.
dipika vijapur: M.
Mayank: The second I connected it to an MCP server, it started a MCP client for LangChain MCP.
dipika vijapur: Server.
Mayank: This got connected to my LangChain server.
Mayank: LinkedIn.
Mayank: server, that thing. And now they both can communicate because they understand their language. So it will ask that, hey, tell me what tools you are having. It was shown in the cloud. When I ask Claude now for something, it can understand, send that request particularly to your client, and then make sure that it is going to the server and everything. That is how it happens.
dipika vijapur: Yeah, so if we don't… if we would not install this MCP client as well, the connector, still the cloud would work, but we would not be sure that it would be.
Mayank: Host directly cannot connect with Church server.
dipika vijapur: So, that means…
Mayank: Claim to you, claim to you.
dipika vijapur: Client, okay.
Mayank: What the he.
dipika vijapur: Yeah, I think.
Mayank: I think you'll start with the year.
dipika vijapur: Client and connector. Connector, matlab, the one which is going to install your client.
Mayank: You can take it like this, madam. Yapeh, in only isko simple connectors bol dia, but these are MCP servers only. So yapeh, matar jaba bisko connect karte ho. Jobi connected dasari, so yapeh run pches run karna bho karna tha. Or bho chhota sa ko denis mein ko jada bho chni hai. It is very simple thing. Tho jo client ho tha hai maara. So jabi hai pad karthi ho, dia ko custom connectors mein.
dipika vijapur: So, these are servers, not clients. So, when we say.
Mayank: When we go to connector, these are MCP servers which we are connected to in a simple sense.
dipika vijapur: Okay, okay, because I'm getting confused between this client, server.
Mayank: Then you need a connector. Connector is just out.
dipika vijapur: Yeah, okay.
Mayank: There is client, server, and host.
dipika vijapur: Correct, yes.
Mayank: Sarwar is there, which you see all here.
dipika vijapur: Correct. Yes.
Mayank: To connect to that, Claude will start up a client.
dipika vijapur: Correct.
Mayank: And Claude is host.
dipika vijapur: Okay. Got it. Now got it.
Mayank: Don't confuse with connectors. Yeah. Let me connect you with another MCP.
Mayank: Okay. Let me start a connector. Let me start a client. That client will talk with this particular server. Yeah.
dipika vijapur: Got it. In terms of what we wrote, we wrote a tool for the MCP server, and that we connected through a client, which was our inspector.
Mayank: Yes, exactly.
dipika vijapur: But…
Mayank: We have just wrote a server.
dipika vijapur: Oh.
Mayank: we don't care, because we don't have to write the client. Client core in Tejaraj is to use container.
dipika vijapur: So, how many… jese postman seam hitkarte, how many inspectors use here to access this server, right?
Mayank: Kind of. Exactly.
dipika vijapur: Okay, yeah.
dipika vijapur: Thank you.
Mayank: Postman also have it. So let me see. Postman also now have MCP. But yeah, that is exactly what you can.
dipika vijapur: Thank you so much. It was a little confusing for me.
Mayank: No worries, it is… it is in the starting, because for us, I am teaching in depth, and these are things which we… if you learn for the first time, no worries. Happy to get in, make.
dipika vijapur: So, thank you, good day.
Mayank: Thank you. Same to you.
Rushabh Parikh: Hello?
Mayank: is the next one minute, one minute. Okay, Nitin, I think you're done, right? People were.
Mayank: Please have your heads.
Vipin Tiwari: Hey, hi.
Mayank: One minute.
Nitin Gupta: Hi.
Mayank: Nitin, you're done, right.
Nitin Gupta: Yes.
Mayank: Rajiv, you are next. Rajiv, Basmanash, Shikha, Vipin, then Rushabh. This is the…
Mayank: Okay. Rajiv.
Rajeev: So, Mayank, you were saying, right, the connector, right? So, I think connector is a client, right, through which, you know, it's trying to connect to my server, right, MCP server, right? Yeah.
Mayank: Again, connectors are just all the MCP servers. When you connect to that server internally, Claude starts a client. Client, it is not visible like a element. It is starting in the backend, which it connects to.
Rajeev: Yeah, but backend is whatever… that is a server, right? For example, if I'm connecting through my Visual Studio, for example, I have application, right? So that is my client, right? But… so whatever in the backend, which is not… there's a black box, that is a server, right?
Mayank: So, it depends. That is based on how we define it. For example, Claude is working. Claude is running on its own server where you are sending the request.
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: It depends on the, it is relative. It actually, it is very relative. For example, for Claude, for Claude, we are a client. Okay. I hope this is clear. For the Claude, we are the client who sends the request, we send the request and it returns back. But when the frame changes, when Claude has to connect to a server, when Claude has to connect to a particular server.
Mayank: This time Claude is like the host plus client. This changes the frame because now Claude is making a request. So whoever makes the request, that is a client and who completes the request, that is a server. In the yellow one, this is client, this is server. In the blue one, this starts off a MCP client.
Mayank: We can understand it like this MCP client, which connects to the server and Claude is the host. This is how it happens. So backend may be wherever Claude is running, whichever server, whichever machine Claude is running, it pops up a MCP client that connects with the server. That's it.
Rajeev: Okay. Yeah, so… so you mentioned, right, another thing, like, you know, suppose, you know, I have, as somebody asked, right, like, suppose I am… I created some tools, okay, MCP tools.
Rajeev: Which is running on my local.
Mayank: Mmhm.
Rajeev: And I want… suppose in my team I have 3 people, right? So I… they want to test that tool. So, can I… can I host that from my laptop so that they can access those?
Mayank: You.
Rajeev: Okay.
Mayank: You can, ideally you can, but then you'll have to keep your laptop always open.
Rajeev: Right, okay. Yeah, but there is a process that can happen, right? That's what I'm asking. So they can access my tool, right?
Mayank: Yeah, Mallab, you just create a gateway through that. Just make sure that you create that securely and everyone can access. If you, I can do that in the next part, next class, where I create a server, I can give everyone the access, so your cloud can also have it. Just that, of course, that might not be the best way, but you can forward a port or you can do the tunneling. That is known as tunneling concept. Ki jape, your local host, it tunnels, creates a tunnel and is available on the web.
Mayank: It is not secure, a lot, but yeah, you can do that.
Rajeev: OK. And how did you connect it, Mayank, that Cloudy desktop? So you just provide those?
Mayank: How do you say?
Rajeev: Connector to the connect.
Mayank: Same, same, exact same. I think my cloud desktop is off. One minute. Motherboard is exactly the same. Cloud desktop is also exactly the same.
Rajeev: So you have to just provide those connector, those details, right?
Mayank: Claude desktop, you want me to show, right?
Rajeev: Yeah, so basically, I have some tools, I'm writing some tools, okay. But I want to test, okay, so…
Mayank: See, you go in here again, connectors, add connectors. Either you can use the one which are given by it, or you can add from the library, or you can add custom connectors, the same thing. Name it remote service. Earlier it was a file. Now they have got it out, actually. So now it is a lot better. Earlier it was a file. You can add the remote MCP server URL, or you can add it like this as well, actually. That is also possible. Earlier it was supported by this only, this MCP JSON.
Mayank: Rather, Claude is having an MCP JSON in the backend, where all the connectors and everything can't be saved and everything, yeah.
Rajeev: Are these MCP are secure, Mac?
Mayank: as secure as you want them to be. It is having authentication and everything. So in that way, it is secure because you are giving it the tooling for traction. It can perform. You can have a rate limiting and everything as well. So in that way, just like any other API server, they are fine.
Rajeev: Yeah, because, you know, due to some expiry reason, right, so…
Mayank: Even though what worse would.
Mayank: Nini Nini, what.
Rajeev: This is some of the MCP server.
Mayank: So again, it depends now on the person who is creating it, how much in-depth knowledge he has. ID is just like an MCP API server. So if your company are fine with API servers.
Mayank: They would be fine with MCP. Just there is one very big caveat that is that yes, the right people should not, sorry, the wrong people should not get access to the MCP server just like an API because then they can do anything on top of that. The Vola caveat is there, which I think will be there anyways. So yeah.
Rajeev: Okay.
Mayank: Otherwise, they are just like a simple thing. You can have an automation and all these things, so it should be fine.
Rajeev: Okay, so whatever we are learning right now, MCP, right, so… so, finally, right, the Agent is going to use, correct? So, are we, like, you know.
Mayank: Yes, yes.
Rajeev: Project or something, you know, where you can…
Mayank: Oh, the project, we will be creating an MCP server which our agent, which we will be giving to our agent. That is why I'm teaching MCP.
Rajeev: Okay. Okay, sure. That's all, man. Thank you.
Mayank: MCP is used in every, every places, so that is why we are coming at LEP. Every framework, every tool, every AI thing can now use MCP.
Rajeev: And one thing, sorry, actually, I forget, right? So, so, so there is a, we already know there is a API, right? Those REST API.
Rajeev: So we have this MCP. So what is the difference? Basically, I know that if you Google, it will say some difference. But what is the difference between those MCP and why I should use basically MCP? One thing I know that agents understand MCP because they understand the context, all those things.
Mayank: It is not that, what I explained. If there is an API, if there are 15 APIs.
Mayank: Will you connect and confirm and maintain 15 APIs?
Rajeev: No, basically, it's not possible.
Mayank: So same thing, ki malab jiti nahi bh.
Rajeev: Mmhm.
Mayank: They are now giving for AI access MCP servers, which you can directly connect. Those are much easier to go through. Those are much in depth and everything. So that is the idea, Matlab, MCP server and API in a very simple sense, they are same just okay, like see APIs are actually the action MCP servers just bind them along with other things, resources, prompts and tools.
Mayank: Actions you can maintain. Just that MCP servers are having a different protocol and it can connect directly with your thing, with your AI chatbot, Claude, everything. API, you will have to define the code and everything. Plus, API will again, then you are handling it. You are maintaining it, you are authenticating, handling security, you are running the code inside it.
Mayank: So that is the difference there, Mutlab. If you're getting a send email API, so first you will be hosting it up, then you will be connecting it to your machine. So it is a multi-step process which you are an SSD taking, right?
Rajeev: Right. But for the MCP also, for example, right, you know, we are connecting to, you know, some of the REST API, okay, internally.
Rajeev: So for that, we are writing those MCP okay.
Mayank: We, but we don't care. Internally, yes, these are APIs, but if you think about it, I don't care. I just tell to my MCP, send an email, and it sends that.
Rajeev: Yeah, correct. But suppose if I'm connecting to my database, right, where there is no MCP tool available.
Mayank: Huh? That I'.
Rajeev: I'm writing a custom code for that, but still I'm not creating MCP tool for that, right?
Rajeev: We have the same thing, payload also, right.
Mayank: Exactly. All this, all these things, all these things seems.
Rajeev: Then why we are saying it's, you know, it's a different, like, still it is taking payload and those things, then.
Mayank: Again, you are confusing between the execution and the concept. See, you are getting APIs, that is all fine. Okay.
Mayank: But can you directly connect those APIs with everyone? Can you give it access to everyone with these APIs? You will have to share lots of things. People will have to write it down at their own end, right?
Mayank: If you are having 10 APIs, okay, people will have to make sure that they're adding them one by one, adding everything, writing the code to hit your APIs.
Mayank: I hope that makes sense. So, see, final outcome is the same. That is not a problem. Send email can be done via API and MCP both. With MCP, what you can do, you can just say to people that, hey, if you want to connect to my DB, just use this MCP server and connect it with your AI. Now, just rather than anyone writing the code, it can use it with AI. So that is the benefit, just nothing else.
Rajeev: But still.
Rajeev: I can do the API also, right? So if, suppose, I can… so nobody can connect to my database directly, right? There will be some, you know, gateway, right?
Mayank: Oh, it will be good to.
Rajeev: So, same thing I can do, I can also, you know, suppose I have, you know, I'm working with that client, I want a client can give the same API to different, different vendor, right, to connect, right, but.
Mayank: Let's look.
Rajeev: You need this gateway. You have to pass this token and all those things. So I think we are doing the same thing on the client MCP tool also. So we have a gateway, so we have to pass those tokens, which also I think we will do the same thing with the API.
Mayank: Yes, exactly the same thing.
Rajeev: So until you see, we are simply connecting those, you know, those REST API on the MCP tool only. But one thing, you know, then why, that's what I'm asking, like, you know, like, we could have directly given those API to that agent and they, right?
Mayank: I will have to maintain a see that is what I'm saying ki if you tell me that Mayank there are 10 APIs which I have created you can use that I will write at my end 10 APIs okay I will I will be calling your APIs right I will have to write something there.
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: I will write a function at least, or maybe let's say a very small application.
Rajeev: Mmhm.
Mayank: How will you make sure that your APIs are very nicely usable by AI? Just answer that. How will you make sure that your APIs are very nicely used by AI? Because now people are using applications with AI only. They might say that, hey, can you go through this DB and tell me what were the last 10 entries, just as an example. In a simple application, if you want to use, okay, it's all fine. You are fine with the API thing, not a problem.
Mayank: So, person wants to use your DB or your APIs with an AI agent or an AI chatbot. How will you support that?
Rajeev: But we can do the same thing, right? So, because right now, with the project which I'm working, right, so they're just putting MCP tool, but it's like, you know, we are using the same API, so.
Mayank: No.
Rajeev: ABC, ABC, you know, they're exposing that particular ABC function outside. They're calling the same in that MCP tool, but only thing, you know, it's like a middleware, it's like, you know…
Rajeev: Between Ajent and the rest, the database, okay?
Mayank: Yeah, exactly. It is a middleware, but don't you think it's a very nice middleware? Like, you can just directly say to people that, hey.
Mayank: That is the benefit. So it is the same execution or the implementation part is the same. At the end of the day, someone will be querying your DB. But if that someone wants to do that via an AI agent or an AI.
Mayank: That is the benefit. So it is the same execution or the implementation part is the same. At the end of the day, someone will be querying your DB. But if that someone wants to do that via an AI agent or an AI chatbot or anything.
Mayank: Then rather than, again, they maintaining those tools or those things, they can, they are much better off with an MCP which you can maintain because when you will be maintaining your server, you can maintain your MCP easily and everyone can just hit that MCP. So it is actually a middleware, just that it makes it much easier to connect with everyday tools and application in our AI. Now, because people are using it inside AI, not with the normal way they used to write the code, right?
Mayank: That is why we need to create an MCP as a middleware, so it is easily accessible to everyone.
Rajeev: Only those agents, because those agents, I think they are more comfortable because, you know.
Mayank: Huh, what the baby.
Rajeev: Interesting. Sure.
Mayank: Exactly. That is the case. Otherwise we will have to, otherwise your user will also have to maintain those APIs and everything which you are giving. And that might be a problem. And that is what I came up with the story. Ki functions dhab, when ChatGPT installed, invented functions, people were using it, but it was scalable. That was not scalable because still they have to maintain this.
Mayank: Now, anything which changes in your APIs, I will have to change at my end, right? If tomorrow you say that, Mehak, I've received the version 2 of my APIs, please don't send the query now like this. Please send it in a divided form. Then what is select which you want to run and then where you want to run it, the date and everything. I will, I will have to do it at my end, right or wrong?
Rajeev: Correct, but I think, you know, suppose, right, suppose I was using ABC API, right, which was taking only one payload, okay.
Rajeev: And the same thing I am passing through that, you know, MCP tool right now.
Rajeev: But suppose tomorrow that API is getting… going to add extra API, extra payload, right? So, again, I have to do the change on the MCP2 also, right?
Mayank: But MCPs and APIs are very, very easily done. If you have written a fast AI server, fast API server.
Mayank: Just in a second, you can create an MCP server with that. So it is able to understand it itself. Mother, when I created my MCP server just right in front of you.
Mayank: I just defined my tool as it is. I didn't write anything, but still it was able to understand it. So when I was writing it, what I mentioned is this thing. When I write in my MCP server tool here, I did not mention, if I do any changes here, automatically I could just change the description. And if I change anything here, see int, let's say you change the payload, right?
Mayank: So my MCP server will get re initialized and see my, AI agents, they will know that, Hey, now it, you need to send three rather than you doing a change here, then you telling me, then I doing the change at my end, then my workflow's failing. Multiple maintenance things are coming up in that sense, right?
Rajeev: Right.
Mayank: And what if that your service is being used by thousands of people? Will all thousands of them change it? So for a single tool, it's never an issue. It's issue at a scalable level, not at all, not otherwise.
Rajeev: Okay.
Mayank: Let's say it is QueryDB, just as an example, QueryDB. It is the same thing. It is QueryDB, and now we can just query the DB the way we want. But the problem is, now when you are doing these changes and everything, your MCP you can maintain so that everyone else can connect to it, rather than you saying that you also maintain an API server to connect with it. That's the problem which MCP solved.
Rajeev: Yeah, correct.
Mayank: So.
Rajeev: Only thing that you told, right, because, you know, we are using, as you know, AI world, right, so…
Mayank: 33.
Rajeev: And those contacts, right? So we are providing those, you said, description, message.
Rajeev: we are providing those contacts, so that's why I think that's… and which, you know, MCP tool understand. That's why I think we are trying to use, you know, this MCP tool framework more.
Mayank: Well, the reason MCP is getting used is because of AI only, nothing else.
Rajeev: That's that's what yeah correct.
Mayank: Nothing else. The reason it is being used was AI only, nothing else.
Rajeev: Correct, correct.
Rajeev: Yeah, Mayank, that's all. Thank you.
Rajeev: Redirect.
Mayank: And Rajiv, to your thing, I understand Pallab. I also thought the same for the longest of the time. I will never post that the U in MCP starts for Usen RT. The U in MCP stands for Usen RT.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, can you hear me?
Mayank: Yes, ma'am, you're on.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah. Just to clarify my understanding, in late '90s, we used to use RPC, then CORBA, then SOAP.
Mayank: then…
Basavanna Olekar: Then like REST API, then Graph, then gRPC.
Mayank: Alright, okay.
Basavanna Olekar: For communicating the data between applications, irrespective of the technology. But when it comes to AI, here we communicate the data between models, tools, and agents. Hence, to have a defined rule, what data need to be exchanged, and the maintenance of the changes and all, to avoid those headaches, we are using MCP in simple words, correct?
Basavanna Olekar: It's a three, it's a kind of a three tire architectural, like, you know, data exchange framework.
Mayank: No, you are making it confusing and complex. You want to use some additional, you want to give your AI additional functionality. For that, you want to give it tools. That is where MCP comes in a picture, which is collection of tools. That simple.
Basavanna Olekar: No, it's not about the tool, it's not about the AI. What is the core intention here? We are trying to use this framework for exchanging our data.
Mayank: No, I would not say it like this. We are using this framework to allow our AI to get context and take actions. That is a much better approach because data.
Basavanna Olekar: Sorry.
Mayank: It's pretty.
Basavanna Olekar: What is the context?
Mayank: Data will be everywhere. So everything is data in that sense though. But to define it in a way that you don't overgeneralize it, I will define it like AI MCP allows my AI to get context, which of course is data and use tools, which of course is via data only, like via sending a call. But I will not say that it is for data exchange, but that overgeneralizes it. It is like saying that, hey, each and every one of us are like made of atoms. Everything is an atom around us. And.
Mayank: Everything is just atom, nothing else, but that is overgeneralizing it. So not to confuse it, let's keep it in the application manner that MCP helps my AI.
Basavanna Olekar: I was more looking at the application side.
Basavanna Olekar: See, when you say like following up with dipika's question, whenever you host your MCP server, it's nothing but the one which is running on your local machine on a certain port, which is nothing but a web application.
Basavanna Olekar: Through which you are going to like, you know, ask one of your client process to send the information to your MCP server, either it is local or remote. Okay, so in this whole life cycle, the only thing what am I trying to do is I am sharing from my host, okay, some kind of a information.
Basavanna Olekar: to the MCP server and the communication happens between MCP client and the MCP server now that data is taken by MCP server process to accordingly make whatever the processing and then return back is is it a simple way of telling like it's a web based three tire architectural process to exchange a data in a very simple way other than data exchange I'm not seeing any other thing.
Mayank: Then, everything is a data exchange. Connecting to DB, connecting to Gmail, everything is a data exchange then.
Basavanna Olekar: Other than that action, what else we are doing here? Nothing else.
Basavanna Olekar: We're doing ice protection.
Mayank: Then in every application in the world, what are we doing instead of data exchange? We are doing that.
Basavanna Olekar: That's why I told, like, you know, data exchange between applications. Here, we are doing between, like, you know, agents or models or tools.
Mayank: Huh, but agents can also be taken up as an application. That is what I'm saying ki your understanding like your technically you are correct, but that is kind of overgeneralizing it.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah.
Mayank: Technically, you are correct, but that is a little bit of overgeneralizing it. We are just doing data exchange. Well, yes, but that data exchange is making us a little bit more active in that sense, exactly what we have to do.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, when you write a program, right, locally, local variables, global variables, session, all those things are fine. I cannot say data exchange there. But if suppose you are writing an application or an agent or a model, I am writing some application agent or a model. How do we exchange? The language should be same. Hence they are trying to use here JSON, whereas in old days they used to use XML. And when you use JSON again, the structure need to be defined so.
Mayank: Data is getting exchanged, yeah. In that way, data is getting exchanged. All good.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, that is a core intention. Okay, my second question was, when is the client process created? Is it like, you know, when the MCP server connection is made, either it is local or remote, correct?
Mayank: When it starts.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, when the client process starts at the host.
Mayank: When the host starts, it sends the request to multiple MCP servers via client to list the tools and everything. Or it can be started during the run as well. So dependent on different host, it can be done in that.
Basavanna Olekar: I didn't get you, actually. See, I'm running in my local host, one MCP host, okay? So when a host is run.
Mayank: Oh.
Basavanna Olekar: It has, say, around two tools, your example. It is serverless.
Mayank: So the server will have to not host.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, server has tools running on the host on the local machine. So when the first question is asked, two plus two, that particular thing is sent from host to a client and client to a server, correct process? And the server process is going to send it to a tool and get the stuff and return back.
Mayank: Yes.
Basavanna Olekar: I was wondering if, in an enterprise organization, say my company, if I create an MCP server.
Mayank: Mmhm.
Basavanna Olekar: There are, like, say, 10,000 employees. Everybody is actively using this particular chatbot prompt or whatever it is. So in that particular case, like, you know, for every client process created at that particular host, should we add a session connection?
Mayank: So whenever your host starts, it starts up a client and it connects with the server. So that.
Basavanna Olekar: How many clients it creates by default? Because you are also asking questions…
Mayank: We're on the Monroe ser.
Basavanna Olekar: And when does the server gets created? Only when the…
Basavanna Olekar: Vismeer.
Mayank: No, no, no, no.
Basavanna Olekar: connection.
Mayank: Let me make it clear. Server gets created based on the owner of the server. Like for example, my server, if I'm having this LangChain server, it is being maintained by LangChain. They are maintaining it. They can keep it there. They can take it down as well. Simple. Just like any other server.
Mayank: Just like any other API server. Okay? Now…
Mayank: For all the people who have connected to your server via their hosts, whenever their host application will start, they will start up a client and send a request that, hey, let's make a connection. I have started. Give me back all the tools. Okay?
Basavanna Olekar: Mmhm.
Mayank: When Claude starts, it sends up a request. It starts up clients, send up a request to every MCP server. Then it gives back the tools and everything. Now, based on in future, whenever the talk will come, whenever there will be a requirement, you will give it to the server. For example, if I ask my AI that, Hey, tell me how's the weather today? It will not go to LangChain then. So not a problem. It is just connected, not going to LangChain. And.
Mayank: Over time, it can do the handshake, it can send the notification, it can get timed out as well. So just like a normal server, it is there. We are kind of connected. We know that, okay, there is a server, it has all the tools. But if the requirement arises, then I will call that server else. It is not a problem.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, the reason behind this, Mayank, was like, you know, I'm trying to understand how the client and the server processes are created and maintained. Does it maintain a shared pool, or else is it a dedicated one-on-one? Because you told one client process.
Mayank: I don'.
Basavanna Olekar: only.
Mayank: So one MCP client will just connect to one MCP server.
Basavanna Olekar: Okay, is there a way we can maintain a pool?
Mayank: pool as.
Basavanna Olekar: For load balancing in the enterprise organization?
Mayank: So that is on your server. The way you maintain an API server and scale it, that is totally on you. If your server is running on a machine which is 4GB and is connecting millions of requests, it will fail. Your MCP server will die down.
Basavanna Olekar: Okay, okay.
Yashwanth Panji: Fine, can I speak? Hello?
Mayank: Just a minute. Anything else, Ms. Munna?
Basavanna Olekar: No, no, that should be fine. I can have a follow-up, like, you know, later on.
Mayank: Yashwanth, you can.
Yashwanth Panji: Yeah, Mike, can you share your screen? I just want, you know, two things.
Mayank: Browser or, that.
Yashwanth Panji: No, your screen, your screen.
Mayank: I actually disconnected the second laptop one minute. Just a minute.
Mayank: Also, I've shared a course, everyone actually just received and sent me this.
Yashwanth Panji: Yeah, yeah, I'm enroll.
Mayank: So Nini, just letting you know that it's a good course. Just if you want to enroll, you can enroll. Abhijit nilogya, I think more coupons are available, so you all can get that. Code or br.
Yashwanth Panji: No, no, no, I just want, you know, see, like, you know, just go to, you know, this icon you search, right? The, you know, the.
Mayank: Oh.
Yashwanth Panji: No, no, what is that software you're.
Mayank: Trikast.
Yashwanth Panji: Oh.
Mayank: Recast.
Yashwanth Panji: Ray Kasta, can you just type in the chat?
Mayank: But after Raycast, it has been sent. So Raycast, then Google Images, then Google Images…
Yashwanth Panji: Whenever I'm doing architecture, right? See, I'll be needing the icon of AI, I'll be needing the.
Yashwanth Panji: icons of this one. Is it only for Mac, or I can… okay, vidcast.
Mayank: It is in Windows, I'm not testing it in Windows.
Yashwanth Panji: And one more thing, see, like, what is the software which you use it for, you know, drawing the rough diagram?
Mayank: I have to find it. It is already installed. I think I set up something. I think there was Epic pin or something which you can use. Epic pin macOS. It was brilliant. It was brilliant macOS scribble. Yeah, I think this was the one.
Yashwanth Panji: Brilliant designer.
Mayank: Brilliant Design download for macOS. Again, I have some software set, like, I have some shortcut set up, like, I think for more than any…
Yashwanth Panji: But the icon, whatever you're searching, is still raycast only.
Mayank: That is my request. This thing is a request. I can search lots of things here, but it's a pity or something. I can search the stocks for Apple.
Yashwanth Panji: I have my Windows platform, you know, you can get me a Windows platform.
Mayank: Windows is there, no? It is a Windows.
Yashwanth Panji: use for, you know, drawing the, you know, things and everything, which is… Excalidra. Excalidra. I have purchased it, but it's free.
Mayank: Scan it.
Yashwanth Panji: Completely get it, huh? Excalibur?
Mayank: I have purchased it, but it's free as well. You can use it for free.
Yashwanth Panji: Fine, so… one more thing, Mayank, say, like, thank you all over Raycast and Excalidra. One more thing is, like, see, like, now we are going to be with MCP, LangChain, LangGraph, and after that, you know, like, I just want to stitch all this together and do one project, Mayank.
Mayank: That is the next part. I've shown you the project already. In the next, in the project we are using LangChain MCP. Langraph we will start afterwards, but for the timing we will do LangChain.
Yashwanth Panji: Okay, but are we touching any cloud parts in our course?
Mayank: Yes, we will be covering, we will be covering projects across all cloud, like at least two projects across all clouds.
Yashwanth Panji: Sure. Okay. Thank you. I'll exit. Yeah.
Mayank: But, madhab, you will have to give me time, because if basics clear, then.
Yashwanth Panji: Yeah, sure, sure, take your time, I'.
Mayank: I'm teaching in depth, so that would be helpful.
Yashwanth Panji: Sure, sure, sure. Thank you. Thanks, Rik.
Mayank: Oh.
Yashwanth Panji: So, yeah.
Mayank: OK, one minute. Next is Shikha.
Shikha: Hi, ma'am.
Mayank: All right.
Shikha: Yeah. So I have two quick questions. Can I share my screen?
Mayank: One minute.
Mayank: I'm promoting you to panelist. You will have to rejoin and then you can share the screen.
Shikha: Okay.
Mayank: Meanwhile, Rushabh or Vipin, you can ask it out.
Rushabh Parikh: Hello?
Mayank: Yes, ma'am.
Rushabh Parikh: Alright.
Mayank: Oh, sorry, yes, Rushab.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes, sir. So, my doubt is, sir, that, first of all, I want to, I'm, I'm very much confused between, host, client, and server, as I was, listening to other people's, answer which you were giving, but still I'm not clear. So, first of all, I, I am telling what I understood, and, please let me correct that better, I'm…
Mayank: No, no, it's easier, I'.
Rushabh Parikh: Yeah, so I'm understanding that MCP is like a set of tools which work for a particular task or a group of tasks. Say, for example, if Gmail is there, then there will be a MCP server which offers us various tools, for example, delete the mail, or write the mail, compose the mail, and many other.
Rushabh Parikh: tools like that, 1520, and when… then we call that, server, then we can get access to that tools. So, is this correct, what I have understood? Yes.
Mayank: Yes, yes.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay, so for example… so then what is client, then, and what is host, then?
Mayank: Let me explain it. See, I hope you're aware about the client server architecture by default, like how you have a client and a server, like that is how the whole thing works, right?
Rushabh Parikh: No, I don't know.
Mayank: Arsha, you know how API works?
Rushabh Parikh: Yeah, I know API, yes.
Mayank: API maybe also have a client and server. You have a server where the API is running. Client is whoever calls that API.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes, yes, yes, yes. That's good. Yes, yes.
Mayank: Now, same thing. MCP is a server.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay.
Mayank: Client is who calls it. Okay?
Mayank: But there's an inherent problem in MCP. MCP now, it gets called with AI, but majorly we use MCP with AI. What do I mean by that? When you go to your cloud and you tell that, hey, can you get the latest news? Or can you search this thing? That is where finally MCP gets called. Okay.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay.
Mayank: So, it understands that, okay, what are the tools which is given, or even if you ask, can you add two numbers? That is how it gets called and everything.
Mayank: I hope this theory is clear.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Mayank: Okay, cool. Now you can use MCP server with Claude. This is clear.
Rushabh Parikh: Mmm… no… how?
Mayank: So you can connect an MCP with Claude inside your Claude in connectors, or otherwise, and you can use.
Rushabh Parikh: Connected.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay. So, sir, my, my question is again, that, that there are tools. In tools also, we can, we are calling the APIs, as you, answered, this, but I, again, I have a question that we have 15 or 20 tools, then, how to manage it. But, in the same thing, in the MCP when we are writing the code, we are also, wrapping it that.
Rushabh Parikh: at the rate MCP dot tool. So, still we are doing the same thing, no? That,
Mayank: Exactly same thing.
Rushabh Parikh: Then, and then what is the use of MCP then?
Mayank: Because if you don't create an MCP, then you will have to create that tool separately. If you are, let's say, using, just as an example, if you are using Claude, Cursor, and VS Code, okay?
Rushabh Parikh: Okay.
Mayank: Or let me not say it like this. Let's say you are using LangChain, AutoGen, and CrewAI.
Mayank: In all three you will be creating those tools? Same tools?
Rushabh Parikh: Okay, yes.
Mayank: How will you, you will be getting them, right?
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Mayank: Now, extrapolated to all the people in the batches, in this batch, let's say more than 9,000 tools we will be creating.
Mayank: Now I extrapolate it to the.
Mayank: Tech world. Billions of Singh for the same thing.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Mayank: Now say that tomorrow, the tools which you have created, let's say for send email, Gmail changed, tweaked a thing in that Gmail said that, Hey, from now on, let people send, not to, but recipient the parameter. Okay. It's a new version. Everyone will have to change that and maintain that, right?
Mayank: So, problem is scaling, what is the problem?
Rushabh Parikh: But sir, when, when in the postman, we are giving the, giving the API, there we, there the client, or that, they don't need to maintain others, we are giving the API, and we are using the Docker, then they can use in, their own, local server, and they can access it. So,
Rushabh Parikh: then what we need to change there, what the others need to change, and what, if we use MCP, then we are not changing it.
Mayank: Do you understand Hindi as well?
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Mayank: There you go. You have to maintain APIs. You have to maintain APIs. You have to maintain APIs. You have to maintain APIs.
Rushabh Parikh: Huh, huh.
Mayank: Let's say that 10,000 people are using our API. Okay.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Mayank: Now, if you change something, all 10,000 of that people will have to change it.
Mayank: Or not. Kaan na pra.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes, yes.
Mayank: Now things like, think like ki if you are similarly having 10 APIs, take care.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Mayank: You want to use it across multiple agentic frameworks, agentic agents or AI chatbot, everything. Ambukar aapko chat GPT mein mein tool use kani hai. Aapko ko define karna padeka. Kapi Asma rahi tool hoti hai. Asma rahiya tool hai dari toolkari kiy.
Mayank: Kuh change ho ka toh ophas kum.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Mayank: Right? Have we looked at.
Mayank: But the scaling level will be a problem. If Gmail doesn't send emails, millions of people will have to change that.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay.
Mayank: Do you have a Gmail MCP server? I have a Gmail MCP server. I have a Gmail MCP.
Mayank: Did you lose it up?
Rushabh Parikh: Okay.
Mayank: OEB AI application, ChatGPT, Claude, if you have MCP servers, LangChain, AutoGen, you can connect your servers and they can be able to work it out. That's the benefit. Final outcome, almost same. But the benefit is that your MCP server, then other people will not have to maintain the functions and everything. You are the main maintainer one. They can just have a client which can hit your services, get the latest information and everything.
Mayank: So it's like a binded tools, binded API calls, which you are maintaining, which everyone else can quickly just use. That is idea.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay. Understood. Okay.
Mayank: Abhi sahi mai ek shoda site hai hai, host aapka jo bhi application jo aap use kar raha hai. Agar aap bin aap application ki use kar raha hai aap seed aap client se kar raha hai. Asahi ghi host chah.
Rushabh Parikh: Hmm. Hmm.
Mayank: Yes, this is the MCP server which is running. This is the MCP client which is running on the MCP server which is running on the MCP server.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay.
Mayank: So, internally, if you have an MCP client, if you have an Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Architecture Arch.
Mayank: So benefit kya wah agar aapne bharatiya MCP server aapna? To aap logo ghost kya kya bharatiya MCP server use karo? Abhi kya warekh kya ji tini bhi API.
Mayank: We know that API servers are linked. We know that API servers are linked. We know that API servers are linked. We know that maintenance is maintenance. We know that MCP servers are linked. We know that adaptability is part of the company's MPP servers. We know that it is exactly the same in our job search. In API servers, there is an extra part of maintenance. MCP servers are not maintenance.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay. So, it is, it is like, mala, it is like that, ja say, LangChain hai, wo hai, say, framework, ja say, kaamkar tai connection mein user, or LLM ko connect connect, that is the same way, analogy we can use here. Am I correct?
Mayank: Nahi, it's different. LangChain jais se tools se connect kartha example kya jaye toh humbu tool ba n.
Rushabh Parikh: Hmm. Okay.
Mayank: MCP may kya waga ki jama blankcheen ko MCP denge? Toh wo, apniya paskey jo banui tools hai wo extract kar leh or toh us kar leh ga.
Mayank: right analogy so langchain yaapi hogya aapka again host langchain kyndar we have a client we have multi client wrapper and multi clients I forget the syntax so wo aapka server is connected let aapka I can show you that actually I guess so yaapi agaram dekhingya to langchain yahi karta langchain to client host kyndar langchain kyndar amarapas.
Mayank: Quick start, custom server. Multi server MCP client. So it is actually a client which supports multiple servers. You give it this thing, then you can get the tools. So if you want to use it, you can use it.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay.
Mayank: So, client venaya, client ko bola get tools karo, client isko jaaki call malaja aur tools get kar dekha. Once it gets the tools, toh phira pusko worker sakte hai. Jabis ko pasab aap agent mein kuch hai te ho, toh agent, phiris ko a.
Rushabh Parikh: Yes.
Rushabh Parikh: So, sir, we don't need to now create the, tools if we call directly the MCP, server client based.
Mayank: It's the same pool.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay, if… other than that, we need to create our custom tools.
Mayank: But otherwise you need a custom tool.
Rushabh Parikh: Okay. Okay.
Rushabh Parikh: Understood. Thank you so much, sir.
Mayank: Thank you. Shikha, you can ask her out.
Shikha: Yes, yeah, man. So, is my screen visible now?
Mayank: Yes, your screen is visible MLOps platform.
Shikha: Yeah, okay, so the assignment that you gave, I just converted it in a way that it can help me, since I'm an AI platform engineer.
Mayank: Nice.
Shikha: So I created the platform for it. Okay. So right now, it has, like, 3 MCPs and 9 tools in total.
Mayank: Well, good.
Shikha: And, yeah, the memory I'm maintaining in Redis.
Shikha: Whatever the banking seed data I downloaded from.
Mayank: Into the.
Mayank: Nice to see you.
Shikha: Postgres. Yes. All of this is in GCP. Now as for whatever the JDs are coming for AI platform rules. I have tried to make sure that I have tracing in Langfield.
Mayank: Thika, this.
Shikha: use cloud. And then they keep asking about evaluation and all. So I've just kept like these things, where I check which particular tool was called per question.
Mayank: Oh.
Shikha: And, like, whether they… we are sending the accurate parameters. Then I have separate LLM to judge the answer, and also checking the cost per request.
Mayank: Okay, but then you have created the complete thing around it.
Shikha: Yes. Now, most of the time they asked me to explain how the evaluation would work. Before deployment, we need to make sure that we thoroughly evaluate the system and then if it passes, then only do the deployment. For now, an evaluation, maybe you'll discuss this later on.
Mayank: Oh, really.
Shikha: Thank you.
Mayank: Later on, yeah.
Shikha: Yeah. For the interviews, I have to prepare it right now, so I'm just asking if you know of, ways how we can evaluate these kind of systems. So these are golden dataset questions which I'm asking.
Mayank: This is my.
Shikha: That's one thing. And another evaluation that I have put in the pipeline is this, which I showed out here. What else could I add? Like something else or is it sufficient?
Mayank: No, there can be more evaluations. It will depend once we run the same, but majorly the direction which you are taking, that is pretty fine. Like that is on the right direction. Evaluation may now comes what are the common things which can be performed. So the problem is evaluation, which is just like testing only, right? But now, since the input can be very much fuzzy in nature, like it can have anything, that is where the problem is.
Mayank: arises a little bit.
Mayank: So that is the note where we have to make sure that yes, we are able to evaluate it better with anything which might come.
Mayank: So that is just something which we need to handle, I guess. That is the major thing which we need to handle. Evaluation by the way, you have created your eval set and everything, that is the right approach. I honestly have to go through the problem statement once, and once we understand that, then we will be able to create more thing around that as well.
Shikha: Yeah, okay.
Mayank: But there can be more evaluations for sure. But we will see that as we move forward. There are more frameworks and all these things as well. So yeah, that should be helpful.
Shikha: Yeah, golden data set is one thing, and then maybe other ways to get it, like cost is one, maybe some more ways would be existing. Because in my previous organization, I had used certain ways, like context is relevant or not, how similar the answer is, those sort of things, but don't know how to integrate in this particular project.
Shikha: Yeah, so in my previous project, like, we were using an external RAG evaluation, I would say, tool. It was called Tonic or something.
Shikha: We used to call it and send our questions and answers from the RAG.
Mayank: And then it.
Shikha: used to send us back 4 parameters, evaluate the response in 5 minutes.
Shikha: Four parameters. So, like, how relevant is the context? How similar is the answer?
Mayank: Mmhm.
Shikha: So those sort of things.
Mayank: Hmm. Okay.
Shikha: Now, like, it's been discarded, so I don't know, like, what are the recent.
Mayank: We will discuss loggers and other RAG evaluation tools depending on the use case.
Shikha: It's not a rack, so I'm not sure even whether we can use that tool, or there's something new in the market that we can use.
Mayank: Sorry, can you repeat it?
Shikha: Yeah, I was saying this… this one is not a rack, so that tool might not be applicable to this. It's just an agent.
Mayank: This will not be applicable. This is projected or not. We have no rag here.
Shikha: Yeah, so just, like, maybe later we can discuss, like.
Mayank: You want to understand what are the better evaluation tools and everything in here, right?
Shikha: Yes, yes, yes.
Mayank: Ashutosh, maybe we'll be discussing evaluation in depth, then it will be clear, but yes, it actually depends. For example, there is no RAG, so no RAG, full RAG eval.
Shikha: Mmm.
Mayank: Otherwise we will just have, I think you have very nicely created the tracing and overall thing. That should be pretty good. But yeah, I think overall the case should be pretty straightforward. So I don't think there should be any problem in that. But once we do evaluation, it depends on the project majorly. Yeah. What exactly is there in the project? So that way I think it will be helpful once we cover this in depth.
Shikha: Yeah, exactly. Another question that I have is regarding MCP. So right now, like, the three MCP I have created is more like the Python functions that we were discussing. If I go here and open any of the MCPs, check balance, let's say, just a cursor executing some SQL.
Mayank: Oh, and the Pika, how makes sense?
Shikha: Yeah, so the interviewer was saying that on… like, it was a company with the Soviet clients, like, everything will be isolated, private.
Mayank: Okay.
Shikha: So, they will be exposing MCP to different customers. So, in that setup, they were saying that what I need to handle will be different authentication, and I need to call real MCPs, like, our own MCPs.
Mayank: Mmhm.
Shikha: So, in that setup, like, they said, can you handle the authentication and other things? So, what sort of projects should I make that I'm familiar with, how people use it in industry-grade applications?
Mayank: Again, let me make it easier. You don't have to do any project or anything. Just normally learn about that, how authentication has happened based on these things, and for the tool.
Shikha: No.
Mayank: So majorly what we will be doing here is that first we will be adding authentication layer to our MCP. Pretty straightforward.
Mayank: Then based on that authentication, I think they wanted that you are giving the access to the relevant tools or maybe the requirement. So that is something which we will just be handling. That is everything which we will be kind of handling and making sure. So that is what they might want to listen that, hey, tomorrow, if there are multiple clients, they are using the same MCP server, how can we handle it? Our MCP server will just grow a lot in that case. I think that is what we will have to handle in that, nothing major else.
Shikha: Yeah, they were talking about some tokens callback URL, let's say, when we call Notion and all, so then we…
Mayank: But that is a, that is a authentication approaches, ki how we have OAuth and all these things, yeah. That is a little bit separate thing, ki how you do the token one, where you have to understand about the authentication things, JWT tokens.
Mayank: how they have the information, how do OAuth to OAuth, and all these things works. So, honestly, I've used them directly, not gone a lot into that one, I'm not into a lot into security side, but yes, that is what you can do there, should not be a problem.
Shikha: Yeah, clear two rounds, so if I clear the final, then they were saying that you need to work on this, so I was thinking if I could get familiar before.
Mayank: I will just suggest you to normally work. It's normal software development side. How does authentication work? JWT tokens, we can send multiple things. Then this token callback thing, which the way most of the authentication happens, except in Claude as well, where it generates.
Mayank: token via that it happens. So just read about them once, just read about the same ones and it should be helpful. It is not very difficult thing. Application is too easy to be very honest.
Shikha: Yes.
Mayank: It just now becomes a little bit more around other parts as well, along with that application and everything. Along with that, why, like, what is the theory and everything behind it? I think that is just the main part there, nothing else.
Shikha: Yeah, because they have AI engineers in their team as well, so maybe they'll be working on actual MCP creation, and I need to…
Shikha: Check on that.
Mayank: So still is expected to know MCP and work on that. So that is the case.
Shikha: Yeah.
Mayank: That is the case. But in interviews, things are difficult, but not in real life. So…
Mayank: Realme, I know that you will be able to do if you have created this thing, but in interview, they just want that. So just tell that, Hey, yes, I've used that. I forget that how it was in depth and everything, or just have a look around it. I think that should be more than enough. Nothing else.
Shikha: Yeah, always. Okay, thanks a lot, and thanks again for wonderful sessions.
Mayank: No worries. Thank you. Pagi MCP learn in depth. I will be teaching in depth. When you will see, I think it will be pretty good.
Shikha: Yeah, sure.
Mayank: Okay, good. Changing back to attendees. Vipin, you can ask it out.
Vipin Tiwari: Hey, May.
Vipin Tiwari: Mank, you're going to teach how to add skills and all, right? In VS Code…
Mayank: Yeah. VS Code Hamada. I will tell you what skills are.
Mayank: And I think Langchain also now supports skills. I have to go through its documentation, but I will cover what skills are not a problem.
Vipin Tiwari: You will cover, right? Yes.
Mayank: Not only VS Code and Copilot, we will see that how we can add skills and everything, right? Claude skills and everything, it is.
Vipin Tiwari: It is, in projects, they are asking, add skills in the code itself.
Mayank: If it's the same thing which I'm saying and you are saying, GitHub, Claude, GitHub Copilot, it can use that skill or maybe Claude or Parasar or everyone. So it is the same thing.
Vipin Tiwari: Have you created any video on YouTube related to that?
Mayank: I have a Claude code video. I've told in depth how you can work on it. Let me share the link. It's very much in depth, so that should be helpful.
Mayank: Specifically, I think for over an hour, I must have talked about skills. So in that case, everything I have talked ki exactly how skills are created, where they are maintained, how you can have it in at an overall workspace level, all these things we have discussed.
Vipin Tiwari: Already discussed, right? At the git label also. M.
Mayank: the GitHub.
Mayank: Copilot level. What exactly? Sorry, git level. What.
Vipin Tiwari: I mean, while writing code, right, in,
Mayank: I mean.
Vipin Tiwari: VS Code that we have connected to GitHub.
Mayank: Mmm.
Vipin Tiwari: And we wanted to add these skills into GitHub so that if developers are creating.
Mayank: I have discussed that. I have discussed that.
Vipin Tiwari: Good.
Mayank: I am not shown that because you will understand if you will see skill. It is just a file plus some extra files. Nothing very difficult. Although you can generally just send it in a pen drive. It is that simple conceptual wise.
Vipin Tiwari: You have also shown how to create a skill as well, right?
Mayank: Everything has been created, shown how you can share it and everything I have talked about. You will get it, that how you can have it fixed to GitHub and everything as well, not a problem. That all thing we have discussed. Now the other skills are sitting on my GitHub as well, so then you should be able to access it, okay?
Vipin Tiwari: Yes, yes, fine, thank you. And another thing I… I saw somewhere another, batch is going to start for FDE role.
Vipin Tiwari: That to be at the same time 8 a.m. to 11 p.m.
Mayank: I think, yes, it is in the morning, honestly, I'm not aware, I'm not taking it. So, let me check the timings just right now, huh?
Vipin Tiwari: Who is going to take? I mean, what.
Mayank: I think Monal and Mapi are going to take it, I'm not going to take it. So… it's 8am to 11am, same timings.
Vipin Tiwari: Same timing, right?
Vipin Tiwari: Fine. Fine, Mayank. Yeah, I'm good. Thank you. Yeah, nice session.
Mayank: Thank you.
D: Hello?
Mayank: Yes, D, you can ask your doctor.
D: Anjani.
Mayank: Devanjan, yes.
D: Yeah, so, yeah, so I have, like, about, you've mentioned that, to say, to say, ask them, ask everyone to send the CV for the job, job.
Mayank: Yes.
D: You mentioned yesterday. So, I mean, are you asking everybody? Because I thought…
Mayank: The relevant people, people who want to apply. Okay.
D: Yep.
Mayank: They are the one which is ended.
D: Yeah, because, well, I do not have any AI experience yet, and I did an MSc, like, 2 years back, but,
Mayank: Like then I will suggest not to apply because a, this is going to be a client facing role. Example client facing role in the sense key. It is not a big company. So yeah, the expectation would be the person knows these things a little bit. It will be difficult to learn on the job.
D: Yeah. Okay.
Mayank: So, if you're having less experience, then I will say ki tuk chau hoda sah, just get that thing done. Because here what will happen is that it will be a client base ki you pick up a project, then you go forward with it and all these things. So, Smith Hoda side will be difficult, honestly.
D: So, and Mayank, I have another question regarding the, upcoming, AP course.
D: So, to give you my background, I have, worked, like, on, the SAS platform, software as a service platform, ServiceNow.
D: So that's for like seven, eight years. And after that, I, I did not, I, I had plant facing experience and, that, but I was not liking to, do that, work. I tried to, switch to AI before, but that did not, I did not succeed in that. So I went to do an MSC,
Mayank: Okay.
D: the computer science, and that's a new thing. So that's, like, two years back, I came back and, joined, like, I had to join my, you know, family business. Okay. So right now, I'm, I'm trying to get back to, industry, and, I'm right now in the career gap, and, right now, I'm having to, like, revise everything and get back to this again.
D: So… so, would you suggest me to take the FD batch, if you have any idea? Because I do not have, any AI experience yet, but I have, like, plant-facing experience, and…
Mayank: Slavus once, just see the slavus once, you will get an idea around it, exactly what all is there. I think then you can take a much better call, if you have to take it or not.
Mayank: The slavers is a little bit different. Plus, as I mentioned, because I'm not teaching it, so you will have to check the slavers once again. What are the things? I cannot give a complete idea. Honestly, I have not seen the same as well. So once I see this, I think I will be able to give you a much better idea there.
Mayank: But I just paced through it. It is a little different. If you have a less AI experience, then I will say it can learn and master AI things first. But again, totally on you. Just seriously, I normally suggest to focus on one course properly. So that is again a little bit of your call. But yeah, just do make sure that yes, at least we are, you are, anything which you're doing, you're doing in depth. So that is just a basic requirement. Very, very basic requirement.
D: Okay. Okay. And, one more thing, you, I asked you yesterday about, for, looking into my, like, VS Code, errors.
Mayank: I thought it was you, huh.
Mayank: We'll.
D: So,
Mayank: I will suggest Kiva delete everything and install it will work. Langchain really should work.
D: No, it should work. I don't know what is happening, so… so I will do that, and…
Mayank: If I get it…
Mayank: Let me know.
D: Yeah, I don't know.
Mayank: No, just send me the email by Tuesday or Wednesday. I will be replying to the emails by Tuesday or Wednesday, so maybe we'.
D: Oh, by the way, sorry, I'm having to ask again. I know you have… before also. Can you please drop your email quickly? Sure, sure.
Mayank: It's complete. Mail to is included. Mail to my color bar is included.
D: Okay.
Mayank: Complete.
D: Yeah, thank you.
Mayank: Thank you. Great. Swapnil.
Swapnil Patil: Yeah, hi, man. Am I.
Mayank: I… yes, open your order book.
Swapnil Patil: Yeah, thank you for the session. I understood why and when to use MCP, just I want to discuss about one of the use case. So, right, right now, I have a use case means, I, I'm working in a company where it, it have a product in, in, in house product. It's a web application where we use a couple of microservices. So, so is mujhapushna tha ki agar.
Swapnil Patil: manjay ik chatbot te argana hai.
Mayank: Mmhm.
Swapnil Patil: agent. And we… we have… Joy ki surf, us web application koi use kartya hai. User application may use kartya hai. So, in that case, otherwise, chatbot will have a nanay. So, directly, woh ik tool create karuna, or woh API call kartke mai, I can… I can use that as a tool in my chatbot, right?
Swapnil Patil: So, in this case, MCP created a build kannikisa padihi kya.
Mayank: No.
Swapnil Patil: Because there is no, scaling ka bhi ji puch hain, or direct web applications hai called karna.
Swapnil Patil: So, MCP ki zaratni paneki, right?
Mayank: No, not at all.
Swapnil Patil: Okay.
Mayank: Nida Jarwat.
Swapnil Patil: Okay, okay, okay.
Swapnil Patil: Okay. That's the question. Actually, there is, the, Amari, Amari manager, I wanna bola ki chatbot there karna hai amara web application. So I will, I, I want to, I want to, create that chatbot of production level. So I, I was just thinking about where to start from, then collecting, requirements or exactly starting from the scratch.
Mayank: Mmm.
Swapnil Patil: And actually, I want to use the land graph to build the same.
Mayank: Line graph queue.
Swapnil Patil: Langchain or LangChain?
Mayank: Arunabh Lanken is good, it's pretty easier compar.
Mayank: If you need more in depth, then I think you should go to LangGraph.
Swapnil Patil: Yeah, so what cons… what requirements should I gather, or should I write down this down to, to…
Mayank: Functional requirement, just think about functionally what is the exact use case.
Swapnil Patil: that…
Swapnil Patil: No.
Mayank: Payment.
Swapnil Patil: Yeah, whether should I go with Langdon or Langdon?
Mayank: Functional requirement, just write it down once. After that.
Mayank: Should be good. Thank you.
Swapnil Patil: Okay. Okay. Okay. I will, I will connect you, Nanette next time regarding the same.
Swapnil Patil: And okay.
Swapnil Patil: Thank you. Thank you, Mike. I will let you. Bye.
Mayank: Nobody's, Hardik.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, I mean.
Hardik Patel: Yeah, Mayank.
Hardik Vora: Up until later.
Mayank: Put in.
Hardik Patel: the maintenance point of view is MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MCP's MC.
Mayank: Neat.
Hardik Patel: You host a time.
Hardik Patel: I'.
Mayank: Maybe we will not have to change.
Hardik Patel: Api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, api, ap.
Mayank: kyo ki, what happened is that, what happened is that MCP mein aapka jaba bhiya karnatya, right?
Hardik Patel: Mmhm.
Mayank: So, on the startup, client gets everything, right? So, the MCP client gets everything. So, it lists me all the tools and everything. So, it updates the MCP server by default, updated information is there.
Hardik Patel: Okay. Okay, okay. You mean to say, jo nahi nahi signature hogis function ki malab API ki wo get kare ga client side. Accordingly, wo work kare ga. So, how many kuch aage dena nahi pade? How many client ko, ya, host ko dena nahi padega change?
Mayank: The example we discussed is LangChain wallah, right? We discussed LangChain MCP server.
Hardik Patel: Oh, oh.
Mayank: So, it's very important to understand that there are a lot of tools out there.
Hardik Patel: Mmm.
Mayank: Aja busko abde k.
Mayank: So Jaisiya Saari started doing it and he said, "It's not true, it's exactly true, it's not true.
Hardik Patel: Signature… signature change, yeah, nayatul adhwatu, correct.
Mayank: Cop.
Hardik Patel: Sanjat me. Okay. Dusav question here, hai, ki, jabhamlok gaya, jabham, client request karta hai, tuus tempe list of tools, list of resources, and list of prompt karta hai. Hindi gaya. So, list of tool mein kuch samajh mein aaya, lekin list of prompt.
Mayank: I will explain it properly. I will create it. No one actually covers that. But when I will explain it, it will be clear.
Hardik Patel: Exactly, exactly. Actually, no one, no one was, was, I mean, I never heard about, resource and prompts.
Mayank: Exactly. We will cover it. Once you create it, then it will be clear.
Hardik Patel: Okay, fine. That's it. Thanks, May.
Mayank: Thank you. Okay, Shubham Rajput dan Hardik Gaurav.
Shubham Rajput: Yeah, I have a link.
Mayank: Hashimoto.
Shubham Rajput: Yeah, so the MCP concepts are clear to me, but I have.
Shubham Rajput: Not related to barriers. Should I ask what?
Mayank: Related to Kayyar.
Shubham Rajput: Yes.
Mayank: Forward us how quickly we can.
Shubham Rajput: Yeah.
Shubham Rajput: So, like, yes, yes, I will take it. So, like, I have one, one and a half year of experience in the software development. So, recently, last year, I moved to the AI domain in our company.
Shubham Rajput: So in our company, just like, like service based company, they're only I am who is working in the AI field. So my doubt is like the, whichever things I learn in the sessions, I will apply those. I, I apply those in my project, which I'm working on.
Shubham Rajput: So, my doubt is, like, there is no senior in my… our company to guide me.
Shubham Rajput: through the AI concept, which I learned.
Shubham Rajput: And apply those in the project, so my doubt is…
Shubham Rajput: Like, how many times should I continue in that company? Like, the, learning-wise, company is good. So, like, should I prepare for the next company, or…
Mayank: Prepare for the company, prepare for the company.
Shubham Rajput: I haven't yet.
Mayank: Much better… it's much better if you have people around you who are smarter than you.
Mayank: Normally, I always… if you're the smartest person in the room, leave the room.
Shubham Rajput: Yeah, so, like, I have one year of one, like, it will be around for the June… July next… next year.
Mayank: Start preparing for the same should be very much helpful, but because I normally feel and found it ki if you're the smartest person in the room, then you are actually in the wrong room.
Mayank: If you have people around you, the whole learning anyway is better, no matter any course, any YouTube, any, anything cannot beat that.
Mayank: So that is the approach.
Shubham Rajput: Yeah, and also one doubt, like, since, in the one year, I've delivered two projects in my company for…
Shubham Rajput: movie recommendation, which we have our company app, movies app, so in that I have implemented the recommendation features.
Mayank: Mmhm.
Shubham Rajput: Based on the user, Tanjad, I'm currently working on the AI voice agent, so… Okay. Should I, like, like, for the, preparing the interview, should I mention those projects in my interview?
Mayank: Sure, of course you can answer that. Anything which you have done in the latest, you should mention that.
Shubham Rajput: Okay, okay. Thank you, Ankur. That's my questions.
Shubham Rajput: Thank you.
Mayank: Thank you, Hardik.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, Mayankoop, nobody's here now.
Mayank: Oh, neat.
Hardik Vora: Actually, Mayank, can you please share your screen of, client host or Sarawala? I have heard many conversations or through that.
Mayank: Can you draw?
Hardik Vora: A cleandrum, yes.
Mayank: Take a minute.
Hardik Vora: Too much information is also worth killing.
Mayank: Oh, Amrulabh, that's fine, don't listen, like, what I explained is more than enough.
Hardik Vora: We're still getting the views. We're still getting the views. We're still getting the views. We're still getting the views. We're still getting the views.
Hardik Vora: I am totally understanding, but the last one which you just explained.
Hardik Vora: Nay, somewhere you… haha, this one, this one, haha, correct, correct.
Hardik Vora: Yes, ma'am.
Mayank: Okay.
Hardik Vora: you fast MCP ka what you have done, right? In the VS Code, that…
Hardik Vora: I've only created a server with two tools.
Mayank: Yes.
Hardik Vora: That's for basic layman understanding.
Mayank: Yeah, it.
Mayank: Anyways, Raymond.
Hardik Vora: I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't.
Mayank: It is a server. It is a server which has started. We have tools, two tools, so proper server.
Mayank: It is a server.
Hardik Vora: Okay. So, Mayank, these two tools which we have created, now, MCP protocol for that local URL creation.
Mayank: Mmm.
Hardik Vora: HTTP 127.4.1 MCP Inspector Apnejuvanai.
Mayank: Mmhm.
Hardik Vora: Toh ab ye, ye kya hai meeraj? Ye client hai ya meeraj ye client. Malab mu.
Mayank: Client.
Hardik Vora: But normally, toh ye host ki waena, humne.
Mayank: No, no, no, no, no. Host, local host, hasn't it? It's a client. It's a host application, right? It's kind of like an AIC server. It's a client, it's easy to reach out and talk to the client.
Hardik Vora: So, mayrajo application IDs hai, wo as a client consider karoon hai?
Mayank: I don't know if it's the same as before. It's the same.
Mayank: We, we AI application use chat, co pilot, Claude.
Hardik Vora: -H.
Mayank: wo aapka host ho gaya, wo MCP kya kya kya kar karta hai, wo MCP kya server se kya karta hai, wo aapka kya client ho server hiya ch.
Mayank: Can you connect to the MCP and add two numbers?
Hardik Vora: Nail accepted.
Mayank: I don't know if it's true or.
Hardik Vora: Claude Millick.
Mayank: Claudio's request was Samjhana, Claudio's request was Akhtadeji, which is MCP helpers. That's why MCP client came to us and said, "Hey, I have.
Mayank: So, I will show you the tools. I will show you the tools. I will show you the tools. I will show you the tools.
Hardik Vora: Nobody, I'm Maarepas to toolshena, tools tab me.
Mayank: Nitin nito aapko dikh rahe hai. Claude ko kaise.
Hardik Vora: Hmm. Okay.
Mayank: Claude ko bata hai na chi na? You have the tools, right? You have the tools, right? You have the tools, right? You have the Claude ko.
Hardik Vora: Mmhm.
Mayank: So much good.
Mayank: Toh jo host ho egha pose ko aap natural language mo sakhtekh bhai merely yeh kar de. Mo sakhtekh sakhtekh client ko bhai jayega, client ko muleka dekh.
Mayank: Can connectors manage connectors? Can you list all my meetings from 10th September to 30th September?
Mayank: Claude kumar noman request yaar host. This naar request samjhi. Ambuya pich dekhnawaag ghiyaar mehpaz yaar yaar sab tools wagar hai. Hindiya pakkare ghagiyaar, meh.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank: Abhiya, abhiya, abhiya, abhiy.
Hardik Vora: Mmm.
Mayank: MCP client has pitched, and the MCP sees it, and the MCP sees it, and the MCP sees it, and the MCP sees it, and the M.
Hardik Vora: Sorry, sorry, my 8.8.
Mayank: But…
Hardik Vora: kya kya kya kya kya k.
Mayank: A client pche manab cloud start karta hai. To connect with the cloud app kais ki pche it will be starting up a client. Jo aap ki server se baad karega.
Hardik Vora: to,
Mayank: It's invis.
Hardik Vora: Apne jaba ko code execute kya tha na, jaise chat server, client server ko call hua, 5 plus 9 jabhija apne. Jaise click kya button pe, toh client ko call hogya hogya. But usme actually wo jo client call hua na, wo apne ko samajh dekhar ho ki wo, usko kesh pakar d.
Mayank: Wo, matlab aage mahapna client maharajan pagar pagar pagar inke bhi yaar hijak kar sakte hai. Abhi ke liye aam mein zoomkar na padekar ke hai, hai ite starting up a client kyunk.
Hardik Vora: But host, abhi aapka apnejjhu pula host hai, to.
Mayank: Oh.
Hardik Vora: But apne plus karke jo connector kartke agar calendar ko enable kya. Toh toh server enable hua. Toh…
Mayank: Server is enabled. Client is enabled. Server is enabled. Server.
Hardik Vora: Server enabled, sorry, my bad.
Mayank: Incredible.
Hardik Vora: Sir, enable ki aki apterpas yebi hai.
Mayank: So when MCP clients start karni, they can buy MCP client kodcha, joh karni narasi karni karni k.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank: To connect to the server, it's very easy to connect to the server. But if you hit the start button, you can see that the server is running. Server returns the response.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Mayank: So you get it. Summary, whatever it is.
Hardik Vora: But aapne, enable kya tha abhi, therbi usye question ky.
Mayank: Kya ki meinos bola nahi aapke ito, ki thum control lehi lehi, ki mein middleware type ho kya nahi koi b tool, ki kind of HI.
Hardik Vora: Achcha cha, okay, needs approval daha. Mujhe laga, already checked.
Mayank: Then, in a minute, I'll put the irrigators pausing in between. So, it's the middle of the area, okay?
Hardik Vora: medieval era.
Mayank: Or…
Hardik Vora: Mohamed, ekor question tha bhi ye jo hum handle kar rahe.
Mayank: No.
Hardik Vora: Abhi fillal code mein. Ab ek bhar code open kar aapka. Ab kar. Anju hamaraa hai, server bhanay tha. Yeah. Toh yahap hamne koi client likhani hai, but internally, aap bulhra ho ki, jaise mein execute kartan wye code, server dot p.
Hardik Vora: usme, wo inspector ki isme, wo call wo.
Mayank: I'm confused over here. I'm not sure what client is doing. Chat is connecting. Chat is connecting. MCP client code is connecting. I'm not sure if it's connecting or not. I'm not sure if it's connecting or not.
Hardik Vora: Nahi toh hum, acha, aap kyo fast MCP mo client bhi banaya tha, toh.
Mayank: Klayani meiner meiner. Kyani me.
Hardik Vora: Anyone, but…
Mayank: MCP Inspector. MCP Inspect.
Hardik Vora: Nini Yeni Bolomi a.
Mayank: annual.
Hardik Vora: Past MCP ka jo website open kya tha nahi.
Mayank: I'll speak lane to you. I'll speak l.
Hardik Vora: Nahi, toh hame, agar hame applications vara n.
Hardik Vora: Humkur to sit server pe, humare tools jo, humare kaam khe hai, jo organizational level pe ya, jo mujhe chahi.
Hardik Vora: Gopali, pure team members kumujhe dena hai. Goyi mein banangga na, toh, ideally.
Mayank: No, it's not.
Hardik Vora: Mmm.
Mayank: So if you have a VS Code in your PC, then you can run it on clients that are running on servers. So it depends on the application. If you have a user-facing application, you can run it on client-facing. For example, you can run VS Code in VS Code.
Mayank: Jaan mein aapki bol naan ki bhai mein ko aik MCP server ad kanda hai. Toh yeh samjhi mein hi request aur uske saab se fir yeh bol hi ki ki achchat hi ki aap mein client shar kar the toh.
Hardik Vora: Tindaman Pan.
Mayank: Agar apuy application ownkar.
Hardik Vora: Mmhm.
Mayank: Aurora aapne k.
Mayank: Usme hogar akhi mein connector adkar. Toh aapko bhi che k.
Hardik Vora: So, madlab inshwat mujhe client saraw dhonu hi mul likhna padega agar ham k.
Mayank: Sarwani nilkhan prasabta. Sar.
Hardik Vora: ni ni, agar existing jo gmail wo sab ni hi karna hai, but hamara kut ky tools, hamara ky k.
Mayank: No, no, no, let's keep it different. Let's keep it different. Agar aap, sidha sidha kesme, agar aap ko, kyi aap ki application pe, yaar ke through, pande hit kar sak hai MCP servers. You are not maintaining or creating any. To aap ko client naar naar naar. Okay?
Hardik Vora: Gotcha, okay.
Mayank: Simple vaishya mai, aapko.
Mayank: Or, let me try to see how it can be created with LangChain. Let's see how it can be created with LangChain. Let's see how it can be created with MCP.
Hardik Vora: Hmmm.
Mayank: Not that I'm aware of, let's ass.
Hardik Vora: Mmm.
Mayank: So, VS Coding vallu ko, sarev client vulani padhing hai on the go. VS Coding vallu ko, on the go client vulani pad.
Mayank: Or a server khadak ya, wah se client na jayegamar easily.
Mayank: To film vocanikal jaga, yo bisaan voim mein duni.
Hardik Vora: To agar hame kisiko jus carwane denaje tossaravananai.
Mayank: Mmhm.
Hardik Vora: Or client k kya bhol hai ha.
Mayank: No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Hardik Vora: Meriya application mein kar MCP for support here to client.
Mayank: Whatever aapko chahiye ki bhi dusne meeri, meeri application normally used kar sakiye without, with AI, so I'.
Hardik Vora: Okay, Rapko.
Mayank: I'm going to go back to the MCP. I'm going to go back to the MCP. I'm going to go back to the MCP. I'm going to go back to the MCP. I'm going to go back.
Mayank: Agar aapko hit khandiya toh bhi, agar aapk.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank: Gaar aapko currencies chahiye toh fin aap. Client bana hogiye johit karega API ko. Kalko ko gaar aapko chahiye gi bhi log meini zero da.
Mayank: Server to same architecture, nothing else.
Hardik Vora: Hmm, hmm. Okay, okay.
Mayank: And that's it.
Hardik Vora: Hmm, I'm a basic Shobhit Samaj.
Mayank: Yeah, yeah.
Hardik Vora: Purnaan kekor question tamira, malab apne jo tools bana hai na.
Hardik Vora: I mean, basically, kya hai, ya, ya, at the rate humne ktools wa nahi humar kartam makars wa nahi hai, or usko hai jage pe rakhi hai, or so that, via API URL, everyone can access it.
Mayank: Okay.
Hardik Vora: Akhivkar and Dekh.
Mayank: Oh, tools here, collection of tools.
Hardik Vora: Mmhm.
Mayank: I think it's…
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Hardik Vora: Aur esko rashtrik mera bhi wohi kwaisyanta, jese ki sine bhi pucha tama bhi wohi sochara dahi, jese ismeh samjho hamne merai k.
Hardik Vora: Yes, server. Pay me jitna bhi tools. Add tools. Add, Subtract, Delete. Subtract, Delete. Subtract, Delete. Subtract, Dele.
Hardik Vora: usme se ek set of department ko mujhe write or edit donu dena hai, or ek kosi view access dena hai. Kuch kaise kar sakte hai, huh?
Mayank: Without the authorization on this, with it being on the different role and add five more tools, we should list, list tool based on the role. Okay, I got authentication.
Mayank: Jambi MCP manta hai to MCP kaise hai, list tools bhi manta hai aap usko override aur okar sa.
Mayank: Aur uske saabse baasiye kya karega? Ki authentication lekha uske check karega. Uske saabse woi tools ki bananyanki ki kita nahi tools hami chahiye kita nahi chahiye.
Mayank: Let me see the code, one minute, take home.
Mayank: Oh, okay. One click.
Mayank: Take a minute.
Mayank: Actually, MCP is an API understanding. So, we have authentication, starting token verification, we can authenticate, but I don't care. So, it's an analyst's token, user's token, and admin's token.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Mayank: I have a user kit who's when I read and numbers.
Hardik Vora: Mmm.
Mayank: Analyst ki tool pone query db calculate average series report. Admin ki tool pone 18.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Mayank: So, widely the merpas nahpi bh.
Hardik Vora: Right. Hmm.
Mayank: MCP tool auth required scope users show information about the authenticated client.
Mayank: Tohun gate kya, uske saabse maine return kya kya.
Hardik Vora: Mmhm.
Mayank: Aur information about the authenticated client. Client token. Aur information about the authenticated client. Client token. Aur information about the client. Aur information about the client. Aur information about the client. Aur information about the client. Aur information about the client. Aur information about the client. Aur information about the client.
Mayank: Toh uske saath se baase hai, baase hai, baase hai, baase hai, baase hai. Toh uske saath se baase hai, baase hai, baase hai, ki lists tools hoti hai. Toh, baase hai, instant hi kyais, maybe. Isn't this directly used.
Hardik Vora: Mmh.
Mayank: Or auth is auth. Jabi authorization check wigi toham tokans ke saathis chek kar denge. Ki client ka ID ke hai. Allske scopes ke ake auske saath.
Mayank: So MCP server kyo kiya internal hai toh yaap nahi test miksha padlegek hai, kya bhi joh bhi scope aauske savse miya internal kara toh hai hai. So you know hai, joh uska scope hai, uske savse it will be able to return the exact tools. It's very simple. It is just like API. You know that API mahab nahi check kya ghi bhi a.
Hardik Vora: -H.
Mayank: Aur uski sabse besampnuskar right to zidi, makki mein excess fat.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Mayank: Kalini, what is your name?
Hardik Vora: Mohammad.
Mayank: Pen.
Hardik Vora: Is Kiw.
Mayank: Me define curry.
Hardik Vora: Watch your step.
Hardik Vora: But yeah, sir, after starting with mobile SIM, it's clear, okay, sir?
Mayank: No, actually, kyanak ki client dikhtani sab nais liye.
Hardik Vora: Ha, toh hum madhwa, hum ko kui esa jesse uska token ID, client ID esa har call pe jata ek hai jo hum ko patat sele ki kya gaya.
Mayank: Purman nikal dunga jata toa. Honestly, padhwat.
Hardik Vora: Let him in.
Mayank: Oh my god.
Hardik Vora: It's a unique client ID called Huta for every.
Mayank: Oh, there we go.
Hardik Vora: To maintain Kartyung internally.
Mayank: Oh.
Mayank: Okay.
Mayank: To make it easier for everyone.
Mayank: Was ki log chinna padenga mein logs Panda najo Claude ki Claude se rikaanwa ki logs ki se Panda naja, wo logs agar hijak.
Hardik Vora: Okay, restricted ka hoo gaya ye hoo gaya? Or,
Hardik Vora: Okay, gitna hi question tha mira. Srikh mira ekor, last question mira ek. Wo data security perspective ki say madab puchne ka matlab mira hai, humjab enable karte hai, jaise Gmail or Osab ko. For this, for example, companies kjo tools hai, Outlook teams, yeah, whatever, Slack. Thi jay, toh wo org level ka jo data rakte hai, or hamara.
Mayank: Kyaise hai, normally APIs handle karte hai, no? Vaisi cheleka saara. Toh jo security protocol.
Hardik Vora: But if you define a third party MCP tools, I mean, yeah, MCP servers use Outlook or.
Mayank: So, it gets authenticated. So, it gets authenticated. So, it gets authenticated.
Hardik Vora: Mmhm.
Mayank: Wo take care kartenge bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansani bhai kansan.
Hardik Vora: Okay. Kaur hamne apne jo api mujhe code dikha hai jo role level ka. To uske andar hum kuch security level pe dal sakte hai, ki restriction…
Mayank: It's a normal server, nothing else.
Mayank: Jitra secured me server ko bin aasek, Jitra secured me server ko bin aasek, Jitra server only. Farega nahi barta. Saar e basic se mein. Bas ek alek ta.
Mayank: patching laga nahi hai, upko rate limiting laga nahi hai, upko DDoS attack kyth hoo kui bhi sh.
Hardik Vora: Prompt engine technique.
Mayank: Sabh, Sabh Kuch.
Hardik Vora: How many Gunpura Manitra in a.
Mayank: Server to ambanari to ambanari to ambanari to ambanari to ambanari to ambanari to ambanari.
Hardik Vora: And Mayank, jo first time tapne jo wolan aki if we have n number of, ya MCP servers jo bihamne wo tools.
Hardik Vora: Indra Ban.
Mayank: Ha ha.
Hardik Vora: First time to go sub load kara ga kyuki hum starting muskuni samja panege. But just in case before agent k basis mein.
Mayank: Naivohamapani applications mein hums kadoor kar sakte hai, wo land chain hum kadoor kar sakte ha.
Hardik Vora: Wo middleware mein karnika ab.
Mayank: Middle area aus mem control kar siya ki kya exactly start waga? Kabuhit.
Hardik Vora: Before AJINTI karna padega na, mai.
Mayank: Oh, before ANIT. Yeah, before a model ku penjnaj na toh bata d.
Hardik Vora: agent ko ekwar samjat nahi denge, ki…
Mayank: Oh, gossip and go from the game.
Mayank: Load therm normally kari lehte. Model ko bhijjan ji meh.
Hardik Vora: Probably.
Mayank: Kuch hai karna mein toh ko jaani n.
Mayank: Both are normal.
Hardik Vora: Basis on context or, uske basis fei, semantics fei, usko aajiv haija naik hi nahi, or kitne tools vejnai.
Hardik Vora: Dishapne woh VIP wala example leh.
Mayank: Oh, World Fantas.
Hardik Vora: Oh.
Mayank: Yes, I.
Hardik Vora: Who, who actual example he, he gave case me. Oh.
Mayank: But the middle way has been more than enough.
Hardik Vora: Okay, okay. Mine. Thanks. Thanks so much.
Hardik Vora: Thanks.
Mayank: Great. So thanks for everyone with that. I think that's all the routes. Please revise the classes. Most probably next weekend we will be cleaning the MCP in depth properly so that you will have a much better idea. Thank you. Bye bye.